<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>a proximate bible</title>
    <description>An arcade of musings from my encouters with curiosity.
</description>
    <link>http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2017 15:20:51 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2017 15:20:51 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Affording Proximity 2.1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For a history of changes incorporated here, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/textpotential/bibliarchic/commits/master/chapt2b.md&quot;&gt;Chapter 2 History&lt;/a&gt;
on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have established interface and user as useful ways to talk about books and reading in our emerging technological landscape, I will move on to explore the value of one particular affordance in interface based on the philosophy of Emmanuel Levinas and particularly his notion of proximity. Pushing proximity beyond its typical connotation of simple physical closeness, I will argue for interfaces that afford both nearness as response-ability and distance as resistance to mastery. This expansion and entanglement of nearness and distance in proximity can help us imagine bible as interface amidst the familiar anxiety of changing notions of nearness and distance as new technologies emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the history of technological change, one of the consistent questions that arises is how to deal with the expanding affordance of nearness offered by new technologies. Nearness in the context of interface typically suggests a spatial or relational contiguity that facilitates easier access to resources or easier exchange of information. Transportation technologies like horses, automobiles, and airplanes effectively increased nearness by decreasing the energy and time required to travel across large distances. Communication technologies such as the telephone, email, and mobile devices have expanded nearness by increasing our ability to communicate across vast distances in short time spans with increasing amounts and types of data. In the realm of bible interfaces, the Codex Sinaiticus Project web interface has brought me as a user much nearer to this 4th century manuscript. First of all, this project brings together fragments of the manuscript into one space of encounter from four different libraries around the world. Instead of traveling to the British Library, the Library of the University of Leipzig, the National Library of Russia in Saint Petersburg, and the Holy Monastery of the God-Trodden Mount Sinai to encounter all of the extant portions of this important codex, I can browse them all from a single web interface on my computer no matter where I am in the world. This aggregation of artifacts into one interface is one form of nearness afforded by digitization of manuscripts and internet technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the collecting of fragments, the Codex Sinaiticus Project website provides high resolution digital images with easy zoom capabilities, transcriptions, english translations, and physical descriptions of each leaf of each quire that is extant. Due to the lighting techniques used to capture the digital images of the manuscript and the zoom capabilities, this interface of the manuscript can offer a user a closer or nearer look at some of the details of the material manuscript that would even be possible handling the manuscript sitting in the reading room of the British Library. Without a doubt, this web interface of Codex Sinaiticus increases nearness by allowing many more people to engage this historic book with ease and by highlighting details of the manuscript that may escape a user participating in other interfaces of the manuscript. In light of the immense benefits provided by this nearness to Codex Sinaiticus, it is also without question a &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; encounter with the manuscript than turning the fragile pages with sterile gloves in a climate controlled reading room at the University of Leipzig. As my colleague Danny Yencich reminded me in a discussion of the digital materiality of the Codex Sinaiticus project, this web interface does not provide a user is an encounter with the spine, covers and binding of this book. Yencich rightfully asks, “Are such paratexts really so unimportant for the study of this book?”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; There are undoubtedly other significant changes in the way we study and imagine this fantastic book in this alternative material interface. What do we lose not experiencing the sound and smell of the page turns or in foregoing the process of turning pages at all? Does the granular access to one leaf at a time shape a different conception of the whole codex and the relationship between the fragments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;growing-anxieties&quot;&gt;Growing Anxieties&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar questions and concerns about the growing affordance of nearness are prevalent in the contemporary debates about the impact of internet, social media, and mobile technologies on human cognition and human relationship. Sherry Turkle has become a prominent public voice in discussions of technology and its social effect, as evidenced in the impressive attention captured by her new book, &lt;em&gt;Reclaiming Conversation: The Power of Talk in a Digital Age&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I first encountered Turkle’s work while engaging a Richard Cohen article, “Ethics and Cybernetics: Levinasian Reflections,” (Cohen 2000) in my struggle with face to face language in online education.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; id=&quot;fnref3&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Using her work from 1995, &lt;em&gt;Life on the Screen&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;#fn4&quot; id=&quot;fnref4&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Cohen offers Turkle as an example of media scholars who champion the advantages of cybernetics and internet communication technologies for redefining subjectivities in the direction of post-modern notions of multiplicity and instability.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn5&quot; id=&quot;fnref5&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkle’s more recent work has shifted focus from this earlier celebration of the fragmented self to a serious anxiety about the effects of robotics and mobile devices on our social capacities as humans (Turkle 2011; Turkle 2015).&lt;a href=&quot;#fn6&quot; id=&quot;fnref6&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Two minutes into a 2015 NPR interview titled ‘Making the Case For Face to Face in an Era of Digital Conversation,’&lt;a href=&quot;#fn7&quot; id=&quot;fnref7&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Turkle suggests that “face to face conversation is the most human and humanizing thing that we do, it’s where we learn to put ourselves in the place of the other.” For many, this phrase, “face to face,” as Turkle uses it has come to represent “real” human interaction as opposed to a weak simulation or even cheap imitation that happens through internet media. In a sense, we could describe Turkle’s concerns as the growing tendency people have to choose one kind of nearness, a thin nearness, over a more “real” and valuable nearness of the so called “face to face.” Stated another way, Turkle warns us of the detrimental effects (greater distance) on personal relationship and intimacy brought about by the ever expanding nearness to information and connection provided by mobile devices and internet technologies. Her provocative suggestion of the negative impact of a mobile phone on the table during an interview is a perfect illustration of this interplay of nearness and distance. The nearness afforded by the mobile phone introduces some distance between the two people sitting in the radio studio together, and this exchange is a net loss in Turkle’s estimation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning more specifically to books and users, Nicholas Carr has been a consistent voice of concern over the increasing nearness of internet reading interfaces. In his more current work, &lt;em&gt;The Glass Cage&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Utopia is Creepy&lt;/em&gt;, Carr continues to provide a useful voice challenging assumptions that the growing ubiquity of internet and computer technologies have a positive impact on human lives.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn8&quot; id=&quot;fnref8&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The book that put Carr on the map, though, was a book specifically about reading and the internet titled &lt;em&gt;The Shallows: What the Internet is Doing to Our Brains&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn9&quot; id=&quot;fnref9&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In this book, Carr’s argument is basically that the distractive hyperlinking affordances of internet reading interfaces is rewiring the human brain to think more shallowly. Carr’s attention to the neuroplasticity of the human brain even in adults and the impact of interface use on the shaping of brain pathways provides an excellent example of the material entanglement that operates in interface. Human brains designed internet reading platforms and these interfaces are now participating in the design of the human brain. Yet, rather than simply pointing to the differences emerging in neural pathways that seem connected to reading on the internet, Carr laments the waning of the codex interface and identifies these new dispositions and brain wirings as “shallow.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn10&quot; id=&quot;fnref10&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carr actually begins his entire analysis with a look back to McLuhan’s most famous book, &lt;em&gt;Understanding Media&lt;/em&gt;, and his most well know aphorism, “the medium is the message.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn11&quot; id=&quot;fnref11&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Although he clearly respects the prescience and value of McLuhan’s work, even using McLuhan’s own language as the subtitle for his prologue, Carr immediately betrays an underlying fear of change and nostalgic anxiety as he emphasizes McLuhan’s polemic against the neutralists without any attention given to McLuhan’s celebration of art and social reorganization in the retribalization made possible by the collapse of time and space brought on by electric technology.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn12&quot; id=&quot;fnref12&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; While Carr gives no attention to this part of McLuhan’s discussion of electric technology, I can’t help but hear echoes of McLuhan’s global village when I read Clay Shirky’s assessment of the internet age in &lt;em&gt;Cognitive Surplus&lt;/em&gt;, which offers a stark and compelling counterpoint to Carr’s pessimism.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn13&quot; id=&quot;fnref13&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Carr leverages McLuhan’s clever and incisive claims about the power of technology in shaping human culture, but all the while operates with a sense that the dangers of digital technology are inevitably fatal. Though McLuhan is exceedingly clear on the risks of technological change and advancement, the tone of &lt;em&gt;Understanding Media&lt;/em&gt; strikes me as loaded with potential and possibility, whereas even Carr’s title spells doom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anxiety that drives Carr’s argument in &lt;em&gt;The Shallows&lt;/em&gt; stems from a loss of the distance provided by the print codex interface. Internet technologies afford increasing nearness with an always expanding set of possible things to engage, such that users can no longer focus in a sustained manner on a singular, linear text. On the contrary, a codex affords a more singular nearness in interface, with covers to mark what is in and what is out typically with some measure of linear progression from beginning to end. In Carr’s imagination, the codex provides a focused and contained nearness that creates a distance from all other things, which in turns facilitates a deep thinking that is more valuable than the shallowness afforded by the internet. Long durations of time and the concept of depth are also forms of distance and Carr finds these affordances of distance in the codex interface. For Carr, the growing ubiquity of internet reading interfaces afford a nearness of multiple foci, shorter durations, and lack of depth that have a decidedly negative impact on human learning and knowledge.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn14&quot; id=&quot;fnref14&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nothing-new&quot;&gt;Nothing New&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his long historical run up to the current media situation of the internet, Carr reminds readers that the anxiety around changes in technology and its impact on the human brain are not at all new. In the 4th century before the common era, as the technology of an alphabet began to take root, writing emerged as a new technology for communication and learning. Following the lead of Walter Ong’s analysis of Plato is his work &lt;em&gt;Orality and Literacy&lt;/em&gt;, Carr points to what seems to be a negative view of writing in &lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt; and more positive views on literacy in &lt;em&gt;The Republic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn15&quot; id=&quot;fnref15&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Ong and Carr reference the well trodden passage from &lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt; that communicates a worry about the impact of writing on memory, since writing affords easy reference to a content set outside the memory of an individual.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn16&quot; id=&quot;fnref16&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Undoubtedly, these reflections on an entirely different time period of major technological transition provide a helpful reminder that these anxieties about emerging technologies are not a new phenomenon. Further reflections on this anxious passage from &lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt; in conversation with other mentions of writing in the Platonic corpus point less to a concern about the difference between internal and external memory technologies and more toward a worry about the impact of writing on dynamic dialog. Lane Wilkinson’s analysis of the views on writing in &lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn17&quot; id=&quot;fnref17&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; points toward a passage shortly following the anxious bit about memory, where Socrates says to Phaedrus,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I cannot help feeling, Phaedrus, that writing is unfortunately like painting; for the creations of the painter have the attitude of life, and yet if you ask them a question they preserve a solemn silence. And the same may be said of speeches. You would imagine that they had intelligence, but if you want to know anything and put a question to one of them, the speaker always gives one unvarying answer. And when they have been once written down they are tumbled about anywhere among those who may or may not understand them, and know not to whom they should reply, to whom not: and, if they are maltreated or abused, they have no parent to protect them; and they cannot protect or defend themselves.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn18&quot; id=&quot;fnref18&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to frame this concern is as an anxiety about the increasing nearness or availability of a written text to a user and the corresponding distancing of the speaker or author. If, as Wilkinson suggests, the primary value operative for Plato is dialog, then writing provided an interface in antiquity that afforded a new kind of nearness to words and ideas that threatened the participation in dialog. Susan Dobra points to a short passage in the “Seventh Letter” that highlights this again, where Plato says, “that is why no intelligent man will ever dare to commit his thoughts to words, still less to words that cannot be changed, as is the case with what is expressed in written characters.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn19&quot; id=&quot;fnref19&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;19&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; As both Wilkinson and Dobra highlight so nicely, it is the fixicity of written text that affords an irresponsible nearness for the reader in exchange for the dynamics of dialog. This concern about the impact of increasing nearness provided by new technologies, particularly the effects it might have on the ambiguity and dynamics of dialog sound similar to Drucker’s questioning of the mechanistic determinism of contemporary interface theories operative in the software world. In a sense, both Plato and Drucker are advocating for a nearness of the subject over the nearness of content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dealing-with-distance&quot;&gt;Dealing with Distance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a much nearer time period, Martin Heidegger delivered a set of lectures just after the second world war addressing the changes in nearness and distance brought about by the rise of mechanical technologies.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn20&quot; id=&quot;fnref20&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; These lectures, know as the Bremen lectures, occurred in Bremen in 1949 as Heidegger’s first public address after the war ended. He begins the lecture series with a clear statement of the issue he is confronting, saying, “All distances in time and space are shrinking.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn21&quot; id=&quot;fnref21&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;21&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The rest of the lecture series explores the changing relationship between distance and nearness with the rise of modern technologies such as airplanes, radio, film, and television.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn22&quot; id=&quot;fnref22&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;22&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Heidegger frames his concern in terms of distance not nearness, because he will redefine nearness as something exceeding the spatial and relational closeness we have been exploring thus far. Distance, for Heidegger remains spatial or relational, while nearness comes to signify an intimate encounter related to truth, which experiences the “actuality” of a thing, and technology does not offer this even as it collapses the distance of space and time.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn23&quot; id=&quot;fnref23&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;23&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In a subtle twist of the more well known title of the expanded version of lecture two, “The Question Concerning Technology,” the concern in these questions about technology is what happens to the possibility of nearness as difference when technologies afford a kind of distancelessness?&lt;a href=&quot;#fn24&quot; id=&quot;fnref24&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Heidegger will go on to articulate the essence of technology as the process that renders all being, humans and nature included, as distanceless without nearness.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn25&quot; id=&quot;fnref25&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;25&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; He begins the second lecture saying, “All mastery of distances brings no nearness at all.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn26&quot; id=&quot;fnref26&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;26&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Though the language is a bit different, the distancelessness that has Heidegger bothered is a historically located version of the anxiety we saw about the affordance of nearness in Plato, Turkle, and Carr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also interested in the impact of these changes in scale of nearness and distance brought on by technologies, another thinker, Roger Silverstone, more recently has taken up this question about distance in relation to internet technologies and cyberspace. Advocating for what he calls “proper distance” as a framework for the possibility of ethics in internet communication technologies, Silverstone argues for the necessity to resist the tendency toward the distancelessness and overnearness possible in emerging technologies as highlighted by Heidegger’s anxieties we have just seen.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn27&quot; id=&quot;fnref27&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;27&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Silverstone offers two important directives in our consideration of nearness and distance in interface. First, challenging the common exhuberance about the possibilities for connection and communication provided by the internet as a kind of nearness, Silverstone champions the value of distance as irreducible difference or even the insistent interruption of connection afforded by internet communication technologies.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn28&quot; id=&quot;fnref28&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;28&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Second, Silverstone signals the usefulness of Emmanuel Levinas’s concept of proximity as a way to consider the difficult tension of contact and separation necessary to afford ethical human relationship in electronically mediated spaces.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn29&quot; id=&quot;fnref29&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;29&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Taking Silverstone’s lead in his helpful corrective to the focus simply on nearness in emerging technologies, I too find Levinasian proximity a valuable framework for exploring even human-machine interface as a constant negotiation of nearness and distance in what can be imagined as contact without grasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;proximity-contact-without-grasp&quot;&gt;Proximity: Contact Without Grasp&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This philosophical notion of subjectivity in Levinas, proximity, can operate explicitly as an affordance offered in interface beyond the human-human ethical encounter. Rather than asking whether emerging technologies are ethical or whether ethical human relationship is possible in our present technological landscape,&lt;a href=&quot;#fn30&quot; id=&quot;fnref30&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I will use the operations of proximity in Levinasian philosophy as a model for exploring the nearness and distance afforded by bible in its many lives as interface. Levinas himself speaks and writes very little about technology explicitly,&lt;a href=&quot;#fn31&quot; id=&quot;fnref31&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;31&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; but his negotiations of nearness and distance in human relationship through his idea of proximity have a great deal to offer our discussions of interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proximity as a different approach to human relationship than ontology or being blossoms in the last of Levinas’s large phiosophical works, &lt;em&gt;Otherwise Than Being&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;a href=&quot;#fn32&quot; id=&quot;fnref32&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Proximity emerges in &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt; as an approach that increases the nearness of responsibility and at the same time increases the distance from mastery. Immediately, we can see here that proximity is not a synonym for nearness and that nearness is no longer simply the opposite of distance. Proximity becomes a problematization of the distance/nearness spatial binary, where both nearness and distance are redefined and enhanced in a process of “approach” that demands responsibility and resists mastery. Levinas writes, “for proximity is not a simply asymptotic approach of its ‘term.’ Its term is not an end. The more I answer the more I am responsible; the more I approach the neighbor with which I am encharged the further away I am.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn33&quot; id=&quot;fnref33&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;33&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this resistance to the asymptote as a metaphor for proximity, Levinas indicates concepts of nearness and distance that are not derived simply from spatial contiguity or its lack. First and foremost, proximity is near as sociality, a “relationship with,” not simply a physical closeness in space and time.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn34&quot; id=&quot;fnref34&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;34&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This “relationship with” is the core of interface as we have defined it in chapter one with the help of Johnna Drucker, so we can already imagine proximity as a kind of interface. The nearness of this proximity, which can not be reduced to physical or cognitive closeness,&lt;a href=&quot;#fn35&quot; id=&quot;fnref35&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;35&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is conceptualized with many other terms by Levinas, such as approach, contact, and responsibility. All of these terms connote a kind of engagement that is a process of being approached by a neighbor or a stranger that demands a response (response-ability) more than an intentionally willed choice to approach another and engage. This nearness in proximity demands participation before there is a choice. In a simple sense, the nearness of proximity describes as a process (approach) of encounter (contact) that demands participation (responsibility).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, the kind of nearness just discussed, a nearness of approach, would involve a demand for an intimate knowledge of the other person to make the “relationship with” of proximity compelling. Yet, Levinas is exploring a nearness that is not dependent on such a knowledge, where approach as response precedes knowing. Here is where distance plays a role in proximity. There are two distances at work in the discussion of proximity in &lt;em&gt;Otherwise than Being.&lt;/em&gt; The first distance is the distance of sight or knowledge or what Levinas phrases as the incomplete objective genitive construction, “consciousness of… .”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn36&quot; id=&quot;fnref36&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;36&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This distance is simply the distance required for a subject to comprehend an object or for the eye to see an object. The nearness of proximity squeezes this distance by enacting a contact that precedes comprehension, an encounter that is blurry. While proximity in a Levinasian sense resists this distance of comprehension through a nearness of sociality not reducible to understanding, another kind of distance emerges.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn37&quot; id=&quot;fnref37&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;37&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This second distance is another way of articulating the difference always at work in this encounter that is proximity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levinas calls this distance “a diachrony without a common present,” which suggests that even the nearness at work in proximity does not actually bring the two terms of this relationship or encounter or interface “together” in any reciprocal way in a shared appearance.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn38&quot; id=&quot;fnref38&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;38&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This distance as diachrony or difference is not somehow an interruption of an original synchrony or sameness, to which a system is hoping to return. Rather, this distance as the ever expanding and insatiable demand by the other consistently troubles any attempts to master the needs of the other. Levinas writes, “The subject is the more responsible the more it answers for, as though the distance between it and the other increased in the measure that proximity was increased.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn39&quot; id=&quot;fnref39&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;39&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This sounds a great deal like Levinas’s reflections on the asymptote metaphor we saw above, where he writes, “The more I answer the more I am responsible; the more I approach the neighbor with which I am encharged the further away I am.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn40&quot; id=&quot;fnref40&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Here, the “further away” that indicates distance refers to the inexhaustibility of the responsibility operative in proximity. At no point, can one draw near enough through the approach of responsibility to master the needs of the other. Instead, as the nearness of proximity increases through response to the demand of the other as encounter, so does the inability to fulfill this demand and thus distance also increases. In short, this distance in proximity is resistance to mastery of the other by either exhausting the demand or returning to a originary synchrony of shared appearance. Proximate distance has no end or beginning, it is anarchic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this Levinasian reconstitution of human subjectivity, proximity is an expansion of both nearness and distance. Nearness is an involvement with the other that is characterized by a distance that resists mastery of the other. As the nearness of response-ability increases, so does the distance of one term’s ability to contain or define the other term in a deterministic and mechanistic manner.The interplay of this nearness and distance involved in the relationship that is proximity enacts both the proximity of contact and the ever ap-proximate response to the demand of the other, because it can never be mastered. This constant entanglement of nearness and distance brings together two other important terms used by Levinas in his explorations of &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, disinterested non-indifference, which I have used as a synonym for proximity. Disinterested describes the difference of distance in dis-inter-esse, interrupting the need for a shared horizon of essence or sameness in order to participate in the relationship of proximity. Non-indifference communicates the engagement or nearness at work in the response-ability in the face of the demand of the other. So, disinterested non-indifference can be translated as distance nearness, both of which are attempts at articulating the operation of proximity as something otherwise than simple spatial contiguity.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn41&quot; id=&quot;fnref41&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;41&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interfacing-proximity&quot;&gt;Interfacing Proximity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can this notion of proximity in human-human interface articulated by Levinas be applied to human-machine interfaces in the context of use of bible? I think it can and Levinas offers at least two hints in this direction. First, as Sean Hand highlights so wonderfully in his analysis of Levinas’s evolving relationship with art, Levinas saw in Paul Celan’s poetry “a language of and for proximity.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn42&quot; id=&quot;fnref42&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;42&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Hand writes, “Levinas’s appreciation of Celan, in contrast [with Heidegger on Hölderlin], emphasizes the poverty, inadequacy and non-radiance of a language, a language that therefore signifies proximity rather than mastery, and a being for the other rather than a world in being.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn43&quot; id=&quot;fnref43&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;43&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Without delving into all of the details of a Levinasian philosophy of art or the ways in which poetry operates in language, we can see here in Hand’s comment and in Levinas’s own reflections on poetry that the nearness and distance of proximity are possible in poetry. Thus, if poetry can be a language of and for proximity, then interface has the potential to operate as a space of and for proximity.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn44&quot; id=&quot;fnref44&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;44&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More specifically related to our questions of bible as a proximate interface, Levinas describes his own relationship with bible as book using language that sounds a great deal like his discussions of proximity. In a set of interviews conducted in 197? on French radio with Philippe Nemo, transcribed in &lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;, Levinas describes his relationship with bible in language that sounds a great deal like the operations of proximity. It was these very interviews that first stimulated my interest in the possibility of bible as a proximate interface. In the early discussions of the first interview, which is titled “Bible and Philosophy,” Levinas describes his view of bible as the book of books, saying, “It is that extraordinary presence of its characters, that ethical plenitude and its mysterious possibilities of exegesis which originally signified transcendence for me. And no less.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn45&quot; id=&quot;fnref45&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;45&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The “extraordinary presence” and “ethical plenitude” Levinas attributes to the bible can be read as synonyms for the nearness and distance of proximity, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extraordinary presence of the biblical characters is not a celebration of the great cloud of witnesses in the biblical stories. Rather, these &lt;em&gt;characters&lt;/em&gt; are the very letters of the text before they are assembled into words and phrases. These characters are &lt;em&gt;present&lt;/em&gt; in ways that are beyond the ordinary, irreducible to the semiotic performance of their combinatorial effects.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn46&quot; id=&quot;fnref46&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;46&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The bible demands a response from its users, a participation that opens to “mysterious possibilities of exegesis.” This nearness of bible suppresses the distance of reading as simple consumption or cognition and begs for an interface of book and user that exceeds comprehension. Ethical plenitude refers not to an abundantly recurring theme of ethics in the content of the biblical writings, but to the inexhaustible resistance to mastery enacted in encounter with this book. As we saw in the distance of proximity, even as a user approaches in response, bible can never be contained and thus will always overflow any possible fixed and stable readings, demanding ever more response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proximity emerges for Levinas as a reflection on human subjectivity and a particular and proximate interface of two humans. Through his reflections on poetry as language and bible as book, we see the operations of proximity at work in a different kind of interface, that between reader and text. Without any attempt or desire to suggest an equivalence between the mechanisms or gravity of human-human interface and user-bible interface, this proximity which entangles nearness and distance can give us a way to think about bible as interface in light of the anxieties around technological change we see throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;affording-proximity&quot;&gt;Affording Proximity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the nearness in proximity is a kind of participatory encounter that demands a response and the distance of proximity inexhaustibly resists mastery of the system, what would it look like for an interface to afford the nearness and distance of proximity? As I said above, looking for affordances of proximity in interface may not enact all of the complex nuances of nearness and distance at work in the encounter with the other as articulated by Levinas. Yet, these ap-proximations of nearness and distance at work in the interfaces which are bible can condition users toward a disposition of proximity in human-human interface, just as bible first signaled transcendence for Levinas.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn47&quot; id=&quot;fnref47&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;47&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interfaces that afford proximity exhibit high surface area, collaborative capacities, and anarchic tendencies. The combination of these characteristics in interface enacts both the response-ability of nearness and the resistance to mastery of distance in proximity. As we begin to consider the characteristics of interface, it is important to remember that both interface and affordance are relational concepts that exceed the material properties of the platform and user involved. So, for example, suggesting that twitter affords proximity because of its incredibly high surface area of 500 million tweets per day&lt;a href=&quot;#fn48&quot; id=&quot;fnref48&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;48&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is less useful than finding proximity in the use of twitter to collaboratively share the location of family members and critically needed relief supplies during Hurricane Sandy on the eastern seaboard of the United States in the Fall of 2012. The platform of Twitter itself is not proximate, but Twitter can afford proximity in particular user interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interfaces with high surface area have many possible points of contact between user and platform. The illustration I often use for high surface area is grinding coffee beans. The finer a coffee beans is ground, the more surface area that gets created for the water to contact and thus the water can draw more flavor from the bean. The expansive points of contact in high surface area interfaces afford the nearness of user interaction and participation as well as the distance of resisting mastery by making it impossible to touch all of the possible contact points. For example, watching a full length feature film straight through on Youtube is a fairly low surface area interface, since the user engages a continuous linear narrative that is taken in as a whole. On the other hand, searching YouTube for clips related to a recent election scandal can offer a high surface area interface through the many ways into the event offered by the search results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collaborative capacities of interfaces offer mechanisms for participation and contact in the process of constructing the space that is interface. Kindle reader on the iphone for example, affords several opportunities for the reader to participate in constructing the interface, such as choosing a font size or a background color for the page. Additionally, Kindle reader allows users to annotate and highlight as they use a book, which can create an entirely new navigation scheme through the material. We find a similar collaborative affordance in the marginalia so popular in medieval manuscripts. These Kindle annotations highlight another aspect of the collaborative capacities of interfaces, the communal process of use. Kindle reader allows users to share their annotations with others and users can enable a feature that will show popular highlights while reading through the book. This popular highlights feature is similar to checking out a book form the library and seeing the markings and highlights left by previous users. The Kindle reader example demonstrates the two layers of nearness operative in the collaborative capacities of proximate interfaces. First, there is a nearness of participation in constructing the material aspects of the interface and second, there is a nearness of community, using and making together not entirely on a user’s own terms.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn49&quot; id=&quot;fnref49&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;49&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third characteristic of proximate interfaces that we will look for is a tendency toward anarchy. Levinas himself, speaks of proximity as anarchic, saying, “Proximity is thus anarchical, a relationship with a singularity without the mediation of any principle, any ideality.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn50&quot; id=&quot;fnref50&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;50&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It is the anarchy of proximity that first drew me to Levinas and it is the anarchy of proximity that offers bible an afterlife in our emerging media age with its proliferation of interfaces. Anarchy in the sense I use it here is something beyond disorder as another order and something significantly more complicated than the simple absence of a beginning or origin. Exploiting the &lt;em&gt;koine&lt;/em&gt; semantic range of αρχη, which can mean beginning and reign, I hear the anarchic as that which is &lt;em&gt;without the reign of an original&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn51&quot; id=&quot;fnref51&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;51&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Just as the distance at work in proximity resists any mastery of the other, anarchy in interface resists the closure or consolidation of use to any mechanistic determinism governed by original author, original version, or final form. Enacting the distance of proximity, anarchy in interface constantly exceeds attempts by users to grasp and order the whole in a stable manner. The Talmudic page provides a beautiful example of anarchy in interface, even in the medium of print. The structure of the Talmudic page is very consistent, with Mishnah and Gemara down the center column and additional commentary around the page from there. Yet, the design of the page does not promote a reconstruction of any original meaning of the biblical text, the mishnah, or its commentary nor does it promote the reign of a single author or principle. Rather, the Talmudic page anarchically invites users to participate in the ongoing process of exploration and conversation.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn52&quot; id=&quot;fnref52&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;52&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Articulating this anarchic sensibility of the Talmud, Jacob Neusner writes, “Every Talmudic tractate–there are thirty-seven of them in the Babylonian Talmud–begins on page 2; there are no page 1s because there is no beginning. Wherever you start your study, you will feel you have joined a conversation which began long before you came along.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fn53&quot; id=&quot;fnref53&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;53&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Of course, every tractate does have a beginning, even if on page 2, and every user does start somewhere. The anarchy of the Talmudic page need not eradicate beginnings, or endings, in order to provide some proximate distance to resist the reign of these originary impulses. In interface, a tendency toward anarchy resists mastery and thus provides the distance of proximity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these three characteristics of proximate interface in mind, surface area, collaboration, and anarchy, we can now move toward looking at the affordances of this proximity in bible as interface throughout its many manifestations in media history. I will first trace the possibilities of proximity in bible as book through an ancient bible manuscript, a critical print edition of bible, and a kindle bible. Once we have seen the operations of nearness and distance in bible as book, I will explore the possible translations of proximity into bible as interface beyond book through manuscript digitization, XML encoding, and application programming interfaces (APIs). Amidst the common fears and anxieties emerging as new technologies threaten the dominance of the codex as our reading interface, attending to the affordance of proximity in bible as interface can help use of bible flourish beyond the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;For the full context of this conversation and quote from Yencich, see “Codex All the Way Down” at http://aproximatebible.postach.io/post/codex-all-the-way-down.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Sherry Turkle, &lt;em&gt;Reclaiming Conversation: The Power of Talk in a Digital Age&lt;/em&gt; (New York: Penguin Books, 2015). For some samples of the attention this book has garnered, see https://storify.com/textpotential/turkle-face-to-face.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Richard A Cohen, “Ethics and Cybernetics: Levinasian Reflections,” &lt;em&gt;Ethics and Information Technology&lt;/em&gt; 2, no. 1 (June 1, 2000): 27–35.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Sherry Turkle, &lt;em&gt;Life on the Screen: Identity in the Age of the Internet&lt;/em&gt; (New York: Simon &amp;amp; Schuster Paperbacks, 2014).&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref4&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Cohen, “Ethics and Cybernetics,” 27 n. 2.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref5&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Sherry Turkle, &lt;em&gt;Alone Together: Why We Expect More from Technology and Less from Each Other&lt;/em&gt; (Cambridge, Mass.: Perseus Books, 2013). Turkle, &lt;em&gt;Reclaiming Conversation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref6&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;http://www.npr.org/2015/09/26/443480452/making-the-case-for-face-to-face-in-an-era-of-digital-conversation&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref7&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Nicholas Carr, &lt;em&gt;The Glass Cage - Automation and Us&lt;/em&gt; (New York: WW NORTON &amp;amp; CO, 2015) and &lt;em&gt;Utopia is Creepy: And Other Provocations&lt;/em&gt; (New York: W W NORTON &amp;amp; CO, 2017).&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref8&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Nicholas Carr, &lt;em&gt;The Shallows: What the Internet Is Doing to Our Brains&lt;/em&gt; (New York: W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Co. Inc., 2010).&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref9&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Carr, &lt;em&gt;The Shallows&lt;/em&gt;, Kindle Locations 1984-1986, writes, “when we go online, we enter an environment that promotes cursory reading, hurried and distracted thinking, and superficial learning. It’s possible to think deeply while surfing the Net, just as it’s possible to think shallowly while reading a book, but that’s not the type of thinking the technology encourages and rewards.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref10&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Marshall McLuhan, Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man, (New York: McGraw-Hill, 1964), 7.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref11&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;McLuhan’s idea of the “global village,” made popular in his earlier book, &lt;em&gt;The Gutenberg Galaxy&lt;/em&gt; (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1962) encapsulates the retribalization process I mention here.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref12&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Clay Shirky, &lt;em&gt;Cognitive Surplus&lt;/em&gt;: Creativity and Generosity in a Connected Age* (New York: Penguin Press, 2010).&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref13&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Carr, &lt;em&gt;The Shallows&lt;/em&gt;, Kindle locations 2812-2814, writes, “What that ancient Roman craftsman wove together when he created the first codex is unstitched. The quiet that was ‘part of the meaning’ of the codex is sacrificed as well. Surrounding every page or snippet of text on Google Book Search is a welter of links, tools, tabs, and ads, each eagerly angling for a share of the reader’s fragmented attention.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref14&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Carr, &lt;em&gt;The Shallows&lt;/em&gt;, Kindle location 953-1016.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref15&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt; 275b; Ong, &lt;em&gt;Orality and Literacy&lt;/em&gt;, 78-81.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref16&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;https://senseandreference.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/reading-writing-and-what-plato-really-thought/ .&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref17&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt; 275d-e&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref18&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seventh Letter&lt;/em&gt; 343; http://www.csuchico.edu/phil/sdobra_mat/platopaper.html.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref19&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The more well know essay by Heidegger, “The Question Concerning Technology” (QCT) is a revised version of the second lecture of this four part lecture series Heidegger gave in Bremen in 1949. Mark Blitz, “Understanding Heidegger on Technology,” The New Atlantis, Winter 2014, http://www.thenewatlantis.com/publications/understanding-heidegger-on-technology, provides a useful exploration of the relationship of QCT to the Bremen lectures and to the larger themes in Heidegger’s work.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref20&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Martin Heidegger, &lt;em&gt;Bremen and Freiburg Lectures: Insight into That Which Is and Basic Principles of Thinking&lt;/em&gt; (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2012), 3.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref21&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Heidegger, &lt;em&gt;Bremen Lectures&lt;/em&gt;, 3&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref22&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Heiegger, &lt;em&gt;Bremen Lectures&lt;/em&gt;, 19, writes, “When we think the thing as thing, then we protect the essence of the thing in the region from where it essences. Thinging is the nearning of world. Nearing is the essence of nearness. Insofar as we protect the thing as thing, we dwell in nearness. The nearing of nearness is the authentic and sole dimension of the mirror-play of the world.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref23&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Heidegger, &lt;em&gt;Bremen Lectures&lt;/em&gt;, 4.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref24&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;For a more exhaustive study of Heidegger’s thinking and writing on technology, Don Ihde, &lt;em&gt;Heidegger’s Technologies: Postphenomenological Perspectives&lt;/em&gt; (New York: Fordham University Press, 2010), offers a thorough contextualization and critique of Heidegger’s views.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref25&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Heidegger, &lt;em&gt;Bremen Lectures&lt;/em&gt;, 23.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref26&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Roger Silverstone, “Proper Distance: Toward an Ethics for Cyberspace,” in &lt;em&gt;Digital Media Revisited: Theoretical and Conceptual Innovation in Digital Domains&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Gunnar Liestøl, Andrew Morrison, and Terje Rasmussen (Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 2003), 469–90.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref27&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Silverstone, “Proper Distance,” 470, 483.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref28&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Silverstone, “Proper Distance,” 474-75.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref29&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;See Lucas Introna, “Phenomenological Approaches to Ethics and Information Technology”, &lt;em&gt;The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; (Summer 2011 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.), URL = &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2011/entries/ethics-it-phenomenology/&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2011/entries/ethics-it-phenomenology/&lt;/a&gt;, for an introduction to these kinds of questions.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref30&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;As Richard Cohen, &lt;em&gt;Ethics and Cybernetics&lt;/em&gt;, 28, notes, the most pivotal chapter of Levinas’s &lt;em&gt;Otherwise than Being&lt;/em&gt;, which is titled “Substitution,” offers a fitting mention of proximity in relationship to terminology we often find in discussions of technology, such as “circulation of information” and “resolved into ‘images.’ After introducing the shortcomings associated with placing consciousness qua knowledge at the foundation of humanness, Levinas, &lt;em&gt;Otherwise Than Being&lt;/em&gt;, 101, articulates an alternative, saying, “In starting with sensibility interpreted not as a knowing but as proximity, in seeking in language contact and sensibility, behind the circulation of information it becomes, we have endeavored to describe subjectivity as irreducible to consciousness and thematization. Proximity appears as the relationship with the other, who cannot be resolved into ”images” or be exposed in a theme. It is the relationship with what is not disproportionate to the arche in thematization, but incommensurable with it, with what does not derive its identity from the kerygmatic logos, and blocks all schematism.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref31&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;Otherwise Than Being&lt;/em&gt;, 16-17, writes, “Everywhere proximity is conceived ontologically, that is, as a limit or complement to the accomplishment of the adventure of essence, which consists in persisting in essence and unfolding immanence, in remaining in an ego, in identity. Proximity remains a distance diminished, an exteriority conjured. The present study sets out to not conceive proximity in function of being.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref32&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, 94.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref33&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, 17, writes, “It figures as what is near in a proximity that counts as sociality, which ‘excites’ by its pure and simple proximity.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref34&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, 48, writes, “An analysis that starts with proximity, irreducible to consciousness of…, and describable, if possible, as an inversion of its intentionality, will recognize this responsibility to be a substitution.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref35&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, 90.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref36&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, 90, writes, “Proximity, suppression of the distance that consciousness of… involves, opens the distance of a diachrony without a common present, where difference is the past that cannot be caught up with, an unimaginable future, the non-representable status of the neighbor behind which I am late and obsessed by the neighbor. This difference is my non-indifference to the other. Proximity is a disturbance of the rememberable time.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref37&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, 90.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref38&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, 139-40. I would argue that Levinas unhelpfully uses proximity as a synonym for nearness in this passage, since proximity is the dual operation of increasing distance and nearness.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref39&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, 94.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref40&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, 139-141.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref41&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, “Being and the Other: On Paul Celan,” 17, writes, “A language of and for proximity–more ancient than that of the ‘truth of Being’ (which it probably bears and supports), the first of languages–response preceding question, responsibility to the neighbor–, making possible through its ‘for the other’ the whole miracle of giving.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref42&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Hand, &lt;em&gt;Emmanuel Levinas&lt;/em&gt;, 77.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref43&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, 192 n. 10, makes another explicit claim for the relationship between poetry and proximity in his discussion of obsession, writing, “But is not the poetry of the world prior to the truth of things, and inseparable from what is proximity par excellence, that of a neighbor, or of the proximity of the neighbor par excellence.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref44&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;, 23.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref45&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In his reflections on revelation in the Jewish tradition, Levinas, &lt;em&gt;Beyond the Verse&lt;/em&gt;, 132, suggests, “It is by going back to the Hebrew text from the translations, vulnerable as they may be, that the strange or mysterious ambiguity or polysemy authorized by the Hebrew syntax is revealed: words coexist rather than immediately being co-ordinated or subordinated with and to one another, contrary to what is predominant in the languages that are said to be developed or functional. This coexistence of words before and irreducible to their coordination is the extraordinary presence of the characters of the bible.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref46&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;See above, Levinas, &lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;, 23.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref47&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;See http://www.internetlivestats.com/twitter-statistics/ for a running counter of tweets sent each day.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref48&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Wikipedia offers another good example of collaborative capacities, where a user can participate in crafting an entry with a team of people from around the globe without any previous “knowledge” or who these partners are. Now, Wikipedia does not necessarily demand participation in the same way that the encounter with the other does in Levinasian subjectivity, because a user can simply take in the content of the page. Yet, again, the possibility of collaboration both in building the entry with strangers and sharing bits of it with others, as an affordance, has the potential to shape a disposition toward response-ability in human-human interface.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref49&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;OTB&lt;/em&gt;, 101.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref50&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Despite the semantic negation built into the word an-archy, I am uninterested in arguing for the absence of original. In my early attempts to articulate this anarchy in the realm of translation studies through a talk titled “From Murder to Anarchy” at the Nida School of Translation Studies 2014, I fear I had fallen into the trap of archaizing the anarchic by arguing for the eradication of the notion of original in the process of translation. The conversations with translators who have spent their lives caring for and working with both biblical and literary texts taught me that we needn’t eschew the presence, value, and operation of an original or source text in the process of translation in order to question said original’s governance over the validity or even methodology of a translation. We can always construct an original given a particular data set and time frame. Instead of eradicating any notion of original, I am asking us to consider a kind of reading, a mode of making, that operates &lt;em&gt;without the reign of an original&lt;/em&gt;. In this vein, anarchy becomes one mechanism for the probabilistic production offered by interfaces that we discussed in chapter 1.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref51&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Levinas, &lt;em&gt;Nine Talmudic Readings&lt;/em&gt;, 5, points toward this anarchic sensibility of the Talmudic page, writing, “The pages of the Talmud, mischevious, laconic in their ironic or dry formulations, but in love with the possible, register an oral tradition and a teaching which came to be written down accidentally. It is important to bring them back to their life of dialog or polemic in which multiple, though not arbitrary, meanings arise and buzz in each saying. These Talmudic pages seek contradiction and expect of a reader freedom, invention and boldness.”&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref52&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Neusner, &lt;em&gt;Invitation to the Talmud: A Teaching Book&lt;/em&gt;, 170. Joel Luri Grishaver, &lt;em&gt;Talmud with Training Wheels&lt;/em&gt;, 13, points out that though Nuesner touches on a truth of Talmudic interface, tractates begin on page 2 also because page 1 was reserved materially for the title page.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref53&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2017 21:57:13 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2017/04/15/Affording-Proximity-21.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2017/04/15/Affording-Proximity-21.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>neuroplasticity, proximity, and neutrality</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The greatest contribution of Nicholas Carr’s book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://a.co/0V05XOK&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Shallows&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; comes from his use of neuroscience to contest any neutralist argument that technologies are neutral tools that only attain value, good or bad, when and how they are used by human agents. Following in the trajectory of Heidegger’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wright.edu/cola/Dept/PHL/Class/P.Internet/PITexts/QCT.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Question Concerning Technology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and McLuhan’s &lt;em&gt;Understanding Media&lt;/em&gt;, Carr’s discussion of human neuroplasticity and the role communication technologies can play in this plasticity offers a strong critique of the neutralist position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lest we imagine the neutralist position as a naive and uncritical approach, I’ll briefly draw our attention to Richard Cohen’s affirmation of the ethical neutrality of cybernetics in his article, “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.springerlink.com/content/jp6227gkg2h01144/&quot;&gt;Ethics and Cybernetics: Levinasian Reflections&lt;/a&gt;.” Demonstrating the complexity of the issue, Cohen begins with two opposing evaluations of the ethical possibilities of internet communication technologies, Turkle’s poststructuralist championing of cybernetic’s potential to destabilize and emphasize difference and Introna’s condemnation of these same technologies for irremediably mediating his idea of Levinasian face-to-face ethical encounter.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Cohen actually accuses both Turkle and Introna of giving too much power to information technology and its role in shaping the human person.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Leveraging the Levinasian concept of proximity, which imagines human encounter as irreducible to the data transfer we often call knowledge or consciousness, Cohen argues that internet communication technologies are neutral with respect to the human person because they simply facilitate information processing, not human sensibility.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Computers simply can not participate in human proximity, which for Levinas and Cohen constitutes ethics, good and bad, and the human person. Thus, cybernetics remain neutral until taken up by human agents in the process of proximity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate Cohen’s attention to the dangers and possibility of internet communication technologies and their relationship to difference and the human person. That thoughtful scholars like Turkle and Introna can reach such different conclusions when critically exploring the same cultural phenomenon, cybernetics, suggests a complexity that deserves analysis. Much like the data processed through the cybernetic infrastructure of the net, the information processed through our neural pathways does not define the human person in its entirety, particularly in the ethical encounter. Yet, internet technologies have at least two effects on proximity as Cohen and Levinas imagine it. Carr convincingly shows that technology can and does shape the trajectories of human neuroplasticity in significant ways. Even if I agree that human selfhood is infinitely irreducible to cognition or consciousness, this does not necessitate the extreme eradication of cognition or knowledge or information processing from having a role in constructing the sensibility and proximity that constitute human encounter. So, in one sense, Cohen’s warning to Turkle and Introna can be seen as one of degree, not kind. One need not take a neutralist stance toward technology to challenge the degree to which some scholars and philosophers allow technologies to determine the human person. Holding Carr and Cohen together, it seems entirely possible, even likely, that the wires of the internet and the wires of the brain both shape and are shaped by the sensibility of human proximity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cohen also highlights a decentering of spatiotemporal proximity. Here again, ideas of entanglement can help. Quantum entanglement asks us to reimagine proximity much like Levinas does. For Levinas, proximity, even the face of the other is not primarily characterized by the phenomenology of perceptual encounter, though it is that in part. Proximity denotes an intersubjective relation that resists the consumptive and homogenizing tendencies of perception and categorical knowledge. Thus, two people in relationship without one subsuming or absorbing the other. In this case, proximity need not be limited to nearness in time or space, but a nearness of relationship with an irreducible distance/difference, thus always proximate and always distinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as Levinasian proximity deemphasizes spatiotemporal nearness and highlights difference in the meaningful relationship between two people, so quantum entanglement demonstrates that spatiotemporal nearness is not a necessary condition for meaningful and ongoing relationship between particles. Once two quantum systems interact, even after separated at large distances, these systems can exhibit ongoing influence on the properties and behavior of one another.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Much like McLuhan imagined nearly 50 years ago, internet communication technologies too have collapsed time and space in some ways as constraints on human encounter, with just the same tension between nearness and difference entangled in Levinas’s idea of proximity. If technology shapes the way humans imagine and construct space and time, how does this not have a significant impact on human sensibility? Here, I agree with Carr’s critique of the neutralists. Technologies are far from neutral, participating in the shaping of the plasticity of our brains and the entanglement of human proximity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next post, I’ll take a brief look at Carr’s helpful use of maps and clocks as examples of technologies that impact the way we imagine the world in significant ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Richard A. Cohen, “Ethics and Cybernetics: Levinasian Reflections,” Ethics and Information Technology 2 (2000): 27. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot; title=&quot;Jump back to footnote 1 in the text&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Cohen, “Ethics and Cybernetics,” 28. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot; title=&quot;Jump back to footnote 2 in the text&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Cohen, “Ethics and Cybernetics,” 35. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot; title=&quot;Jump back to footnote 3 in the text&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;See Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy entry on “&lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/qt-entangle/&quot;&gt;Quantum Entanglement and Information&lt;/a&gt;,” where Schrödinger is quoted saying, “When two systems, of which we know the states by their respective representatives, enter into temporary physical interaction due to known forces between them, and when after a time of mutual influence the systems separate again, then they can no longer be described in the same way as before, viz. by endowing each of them with a representative of its own. I would not call that one but rather the characteristic trait of quantum mechanics, the one that enforces its entire departure from classical lines of thought. By the interaction the two representatives [the quantum states] have become entangled.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot; title=&quot;Jump back to footnote 4 in the text&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 09:27:28 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2017/02/14/neuroplasticity-proximity-and-neutrality.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2017/02/14/neuroplasticity-proximity-and-neutrality.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>chapter 1 - interface</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;face-to-face&quot;&gt;face to face&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would I suggest that bible or book could be thought of as an interface? Often, we associate interface with digital technologies. Human Computer Interface (HCI) and Graphical User Interface (GUI) have become major area of study and discourse in the world of software design. Yet, the word ‘face’ has come to signify human interaction unmediated by digital technologies in the common phrase ‘face to face.’ There is a great deal of discussion these days about the different values of online/virtual/digital interaction and the so-called ‘face to face.’ For example, Sherry Turkle has become a prominent public voice in discussions of technology and its social effect, as evidenced in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://
storify.com/textpotential/turkle-face-to-face&quot;&gt;impressive attention&lt;/a&gt; captured by her new book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/1594205558&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reclaiming Conversation: The Power of Talk in a Digital Age&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I first encountered Turkle’s work while engaging a Richard Cohen article, ’&lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/A:1010060128998&quot;&gt;Ethics and Cybernetics: Levinasian Reflections&lt;/a&gt;,’ in my struggle with the face to face language in online education. Using her work from 1995, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/B004V3WQXG&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Life on the Screen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Cohen offers Turkle as an example of media scholars who champion the advantages of cybernetics and internet communication technologies for redefining subjectivities in the direction of post-modern notions of multiplicity and instability (Cohen, ‘Ethics and Cybernetics,’ 27, n. 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkle’s more recent work (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/B004DL0KW0&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alone Together&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/1594205558&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reclaiming Conversation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) has shifted focus from this earlier celebration of the fragmented self to a serious anxiety about the effects of robotics and mobile devices on our social capacities as humans. Two minutes into a 2015 NPR interview titled ’&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/2015/09/26/443480452/making-the-case-for-face-to-face-in-an-era-of-digital-conversation&quot;&gt;Making the Case For Face to Face in an Era of Digital Conversation&lt;/a&gt;,’ Turkle suggests that ‘face to face conversation is the most human and humanizing thing that we do, it’s where we learn to put ourselves in the place of the other.’ For many, this phrase, ‘face to face,’ as Turkle uses it has come to represent ‘real’ human interaction as opposed to a weak simulation or even cheap imitation that happens through internet media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of why the language of inter&lt;em&gt;face&lt;/em&gt; compels me is because it can unsettle this binary between digital interfaces and this ‘face to face’ advocated by Turkle. Conversation over the coffee table and exchanges on Twitter can both be understood as interface and both are mediated by technologies if we understand language as a technology. So, this term, ‘interface,’ pushes beyond any digital/analog or virtual/real dichotomies and demands that we think about interface design in whatever media we find ourselves using. In a way, we could imagine ‘interface,’ the intersection of faces, as a useful translation of the phrase ‘face to face.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at the basic uses of ‘interface’ in the English language, we can see the strong indication of interaction and connection as well as the prevalent use in the computing arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/ee8abe5e-d686-4d75-9750-aef440f68ee2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Google Search, ’&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=interface+definition&quot;&gt;interface definition&lt;/a&gt;’)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in these definitions, we can see that the ‘face to face’ championed by Turkle and others can easily fit into the notion of interface as ‘a point where two subjects meet or interact.’ When I take up the language of interface, I am not limiting our conversation to digital technologies that afford human interaction with machines. I hope to explore interface as a broader category for spaces of encounter that include many forms of media and mediation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;zone-of-encounter&quot;&gt;zone of encounter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Johanna Drucker offers an approach to interface that fits well with this idea of spaces of encounter. In her essay, ‘Humanities Approaches to Interface Theory,’ Drucker helpfully intertwines digital media studies explorations of interface design with humanities questions of subjectivity. In an exemplary fashion, Drucker demonstrates a reflexive practice by stating her desire to explore the theory undergirding her own scholarly working environments at the cusp of a transition from print to other dominant media/interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/3baec621-ff12-4b1e-acbe-d84a8d06c6f5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Drucker, ’&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.culturemachine.net/index.php/cm/issue/view/23&quot;&gt;Interface Theory&lt;/a&gt;’, 2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drucker shows her awareness of the shifts at work in the emerging digital media age and asks us as humanists to become a part of the process of constructing a theory to support the design of our reading and writing spaces as a counter balance to the often mechanistic principles at work in software design (Drucker, ‘Interface Theory,’ 1-2). I see this project as contributing to these efforts and I am grateful for the challenge from Drucker and others. As she looks to GIS, social networking, and visualization for hints of new possibilities, we may even look back into print technologies (e.g. Talmudic page) for some suggestions toward interface design that might afford a bible textual apparatus that is ‘constellationary, distributed, and multi-faceted.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combining graphical reading analysis, frame analysis, and a constructivist model of subjectivity, Drucker gives us a view of interface as more of a theatre than a window (Drucker, ’&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.culturemachine.net/index.php/cm/issue/view/23&quot;&gt;Interface Theory&lt;/a&gt;’, 9).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/a68e3f9b-626d-45c0-b3b4-115bffdc7df7.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Drucker, ‘Interface Theory,’ 9)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of a thing, interface is a zone of encounter. So, if we turn toward books and reading more specifically, ’Interface is &lt;em&gt;what we read&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;how we read&lt;/em&gt; combined through engagement’ (Drucker, ‘Interface Theory,’ 9). This is a critical point in the relationship of bible and/as media. If an interface involves both what we read and how we read, the design of the book technologies we use when reading shapes the reading performance and meaning made as much as the content. Reading bible in a codex is a different zone of encounter than reading bible on an iPhone, thus, both the book and the reader are constituted differently in these two interfaces. This means that the transitions from scroll to codex and codex to internet are not simply new ways of reading the same content. Rather, bible and reader are both transformed in the new space of encounter made possible by these different interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to state the importance of interface in the reading process is to suggest that the structures of a particular book technology ARE information, not merely a means of access to information. This is another way of bothering the dichotomy between form and content or medium and message. In this interface as zone of encounter, medium and message are so inextricably entangled that attempting to tease them apart is futile. Drucker highlights this well, saying,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/69b6b4de-5c3f-4634-9239-63f053a3a726.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Drucker, ‘Interface Theory,’ 10)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, the ‘page’ (interesting that this structure of page persists into the internet ecosystem. Perhaps more evidence of the palimpsestuous nature of media translations) is not simply a window through which a user accesses data. Rather, the page is a part of the data and the data, in part, structures the page. So, with a codex, the space of the page is part of the data of the text, not simply a delivery mechanism. The shift from zone to space in Drucker’s language here, particularly a space that is something other than a space ‘between,’ surfaces a potential contact between interface and thirdspace in Edward Soja.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interface-as-thirdspace&quot;&gt;interface as thirdspace&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drucker is mostly focused on scholarly reading and writing practices and the role of the human subject in the construction of these spaces. If interface is a space of encounter, but something more than simply a space between, then we can imagine resonances between Drucker’s interface theory and Edward Soja’s notion of thirdspace. Interface as space can push beyond the intersection of two systems toward creating spaces that Foster emergence. As I mentioned earlier, the term ‘interface’ has the potential to challenge the binary struggle between both the virtual (digital) and real (face to face) and the what and the how of reading practice. One of the most important operations of thirdspace for Soja is to challenge any form of cultural inquiry that reduces to binaries, so Druker’s interface is already participating in a value of thirdspace. In fact, the subtitle of Soja’s &lt;em&gt;Thirdspace&lt;/em&gt; holds together the terms of this virtual/real binary by exploring ‘real–and–imagined places.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soja builds off of Henri Lefebvre’s work in &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.com/0631181776&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Production of Space&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to suggest an important role for spatiality in the process of cultural meaning making. Soja begins his introduction with a focus on participatory construction of space which sounds like the practice of interface in Drucker:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/a07d681d-87dc-48af-8a0b-58dc9c091b25.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Soja, &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.com/1557866759&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdspace&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea that we are “intrinsically spatial beings” is one example of Drucker’s suggestion of a constructivist subjectivity. For both Soja and Drucker it is not simply that we together construct space but also that spaces construct us as we construct spaces. Soja’s mention of social consequences here makes me think of Marsh McLuhan’s famous adage that the medium is the message. Though often misunderstood as reductionist or absolutist, McLuhan is simply suggesting that the message of any medium is its social effect not the content it contains (McLuhan, &lt;em&gt;Understanding Media&lt;/em&gt;, 8). Both Soja and Drucker do us a favor to remind us that our materiality which can be called media or can be called spatiality has a significant impact on our sociality. This is precisely what I hear McLuhan saying in the medium is the message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, Drucker’s notion of interface already challenges binaries and encourages a more spatial and material and constructed notion of both media and the subject. So, why add thirdspace into the mix? What Soja’a thirdspace ads to our emerging theory of interface is his approach of ‘thirding as Othering,’ which practices an infinite preference for an alternative when faced with a binary choice (Soja, ’&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/1229393&quot;&gt;Afterword&lt;/a&gt;,’ 1421). This explicit and intentional methodology of surfacing multiplicity when faced with a binary may not guide interface design or theory like it does Soja’s cultural critique. Yet, what I hear in Lefebvre’s &lt;em&gt;il y a toujour l’Autre&lt;/em&gt; and in Soja’s thirding-as-Othering is a disposition toward emergence of the chaotic kind, alternatives that challenge established categories and resist closed analysis without a need to eradicate these categories. Interface as thirdspace pushes the multiplicity Drucker encourages in her framing of interface toward a property of emergence in interface that will always overflow our analysis. Drucker says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/0300dac1-854e-4feb-8be3-692538c3b369.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Drucker resists the strictly functional and mechanistic theories of interface design and asks humanists to imagine something more variable and responsive to the particularities of the people and the spaces involved in interface. Interface as thirdspace suggests that even these combinatorial particularities do not produce the total set of possibilities, ‘there is always an-Other.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interface-as-translation&quot;&gt;interface as translation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;???
– with Piotr Blumczynski’s new book Ubiquitous Translation and the focus on the WHAT and HOW, I feel like I could link the WHAT and HOW of reading in Drucker to the WHAT and HOW of translation and suggest that interface is a kind of translational event. In a sense then, we have at least two kinds of translations going on with bible, a material media translation of book from print codex to mobile phone as well as the translational act that is interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;book-as-interface&quot;&gt;book as interface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we have moved from the mechanistic idea of interface as a thing through which we view data, to a constructivist interface as a zone of encounter that constitutes a space and a subject, finally to a spatial interface as thirdspace with a disposition toward interruptive emergence. The important strand that follows this trajectory is the continued challenge to any compartmentalization of what and how we read. Just as interface is not simply a thing we look through, a book is not just a container for content. A book is an invitation to an encounter in the practice of reading and the materiality of this encounter has as much to tell us about meaning as the stories we read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near the end of her exhortation to humanities scholars to take seriously the task of building a theory of interface, Drucker reminds us that book has always been an interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/518ee2c8-8c63-43c0-b171-10aa00e70679.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Drucker, ‘Interface Theory,’ 18)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quote Drucker here at length for two reasons. First, I have at times been prone to and accused of the charming ‘strict binarisms and technophilic exuberance’ Drucker cautions of here. Though I have found hyperbolic rhetoric useful at times to unsettle our unquestioned assumptions about media, I want to be exceedingly clear that, with Drucker, I am not interested in propagating some old/new hierarchical dichotomy between codex and emerging book technologies. This is why I began with material media translation as a palimpsest in my introduction. Each emerging book technology is a translation of what came before it, a writing over that never fully replicates and only partially erases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, this passage from Drucker begins and ends with a reminder that book has always been an interface. As the materiality of this interface shifts, we will undoubtedly learn from previous forms as we explore the affordances of emerging technologies. The last full sentence of this passage captures nicely the importance of understanding book as interface. To paraphrase in alliterative fashion, Drucker suggests that a book is an interface that &lt;strong&gt;provokes probabilistic production&lt;/strong&gt; through the reading event (Drucker, ‘Interface Theory,’ 18). Let’s look closely at each of these p-words in reverse order, production, probabilistic, and provokes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;production&quot;&gt;production&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drucker continues to pound home her constructivist approach to both subject and text by reiterating that a text or work is &lt;em&gt;produced&lt;/em&gt; in the encounter facilitated by the book. This is another way of stating that book is not simply a window or a container through which we access and consume a text. Rather, book is a space (is it too reductionist to correlate space and ‘a structured environment’ in Drucker?) that begs an encounter between reader and the structured environment of the interface and more. Drucker’s foregrounding of reading as production rather than simple consumption of a text reminds me of the problematization of the production/consumption binary in Michel de Certeau’s work, &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.com/0520271459&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Practice of Everyday Life&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De Certeau’s explorations of ‘the practice of everyday life’ respect the deep concerns about commodification so well articulated by many materialist critiques of culture, yet questions the often accompanying low view of mass culture and pessimism concerning the everyman. De Certeau restores some poetic dignity to the masses by reframing consumption as &lt;em&gt;production&lt;/em&gt;, giving each person in each moment an agency in the meaning making endeavor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/92953a97-7d17-4694-978f-09b01d794357.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Rendall translating de Certeau, &lt;em&gt;Practice,&lt;/em&gt; xviii)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not explicitly taking up the power dynamics de Certeau so beautifully explores in this work. Yet, his consistent challenge of the production/consumption binary without erasing the role of the structures or the participation of the ‘consumer’ reinforces our approach here of book as interface that provokes production. De Certeau also helpfully reminds me that book as interface does not necessarily erase the operations of book as container. The container attributes of book remain as a part of the material structures that constitute the potential productive space of the interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De Certeau uses reading as one of his examples of “everyday practices that produce without capitalizing” (Rendall translating de Certeau, &lt;em&gt;Practice&lt;/em&gt;, xx). He notes the often assumed writing-reading binary as a specific example of the production-consumption binary, but articulates a notion of reading that can not be reduced to this dichotomy. Reading is a “silent production” (xxi), “a play of spaces” (xxi), “an ‘art’ which is anything but passive” (xxii), and most poingnantly, reading “transforms another person’s property into a space borrowed for a mo-ment by a transient” (xxi). Reading as everyday practice is a poiesis, a making, within structured constraints that resists the production-consumption binary and thus offers a notion of reading as encounter that produces both the reader and the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;probabilistic&quot;&gt;probabilistic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an essay titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/13534640903208834&quot;&gt;‘Entity to Event: From Literal, Mechanistic Materiality to Probabilistic Materiality,’&lt;/a&gt; Drucker expounds in much more detail her use of the term probabilistic as it relates to reading interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/33694b6f-b774-453f-908f-1faa103ab42e.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Drucker, ‘Entity to Event,’ 8)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can tell even in ‘Interface Theory,’ that probabilistic is an alternative to mechanistic for Drucker in her analysis of the shortcomings of interface design as driven by the software development world (Drucker, ‘Interface Theory,’ 10). Here, in this passage from ‘Entity to Event,’ with its strange alignment, we can see her ability to both show and tell the role of materiality in the reading event. This claim of event rather than entity is parallel to my suggestion that book as interface is an encounter not just a container. The basic distinction between the mechanistic and the probabilistic for Drucker is that the former attempts to present a user with an entity to consume, while the latter presents the reader with a set of possibilities that condition at reading event that will inevitably be new every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/a7eaaeda-d373-49cf-97cc-ce431a87b93b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Drucker, ‘Entity to Event,’ 14)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This points back, in a way, to the interruptive emergence we found in Soja’s notion of thirdspace and begs a further discussion about the role of complexity theory in Drucker’s concept of interface as event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;MORE ON COMPLEXITY, PROBABILITY, AND EMERGENCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than simply presenting a user with an entity to consume, a probabilistic materiality of interface &lt;em&gt;provokes&lt;/em&gt; production of both text and subject in the practice of reading. Let’s look more closely at the provocation of interface, which Drucker suggests is related to the cues and clues an interface offers for the performance of a text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;provoke&quot;&gt;provoke&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love that Drucker celebrates the provocation of reading interfaces. A codex doesn’t simply lay passive on the shelf waiting to be opened and penetrated by the reader. The materiality of the book as interface participates in and even provokes a reading event. A page from a book in Amazon reader on my iPhone, which gives me as reader all kinds of power over the page, provokes a possibility set of reading tactics, even if not entirely determinative. Book as container just waits to be consumed, book as interface provokes encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This provocation reminds us that interface is an active participant as structured environment in the production of meaning that is a reading event. One way to talk about the material dispositions of an interface is through affordances. Affordances are the set of real or perceived use possibilities offered by the material design of an interface &lt;em&gt;in relationship to a particular user and context&lt;/em&gt;. The history of the term affordance is well established, beginning with James J. Gibson in the field of psychology and brought into the realm of HCI through Donald Norman’s book &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Psychology of Everyday Things&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is charmingly known as POET.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;See McGrenere and Ho, ’&lt;a href=&quot;http://teaching.polishedsolid.com/spring2006/iti/read/affordances.pdf&quot;&gt;Affordances: Clarifying and Evolving a Concept&lt;/a&gt;,’ 1, for a brief history of the use of the term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/bf9e5447-4d12-4831-aacc-0dbcbbbcbf1a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Norman, POET, 9)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what Norman offers as a definition of affordance. As McGrenere and Ho demonstrate, there is a lot of debate and extension around this definition. For our purposes, the importance of affordance is that there are material properties of an interface that present a possibility set of uses to a reader. This is different than affordances ‘determining’ the reading event or even the total set of possibilities for use. Here, I prefer to reach back to Gibson’s use of affordance in that he defines affordance realtionally. MORE…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Affordances as a set of possibilities in a given field remind me of Pierre Bourdieu’s notion of habitus. Contrast the set of structures/possibilities in interface affordance to the structuring structures that present a subject with a possibility set in a field. Neither are determinative for practice, but they do shape the space significantly. MORE…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pathways&quot;&gt;pathways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pathways project
Thankfully, we already have some compelling and instructive examples of people trying to design book as interface in our emerging media age. John Miles Foley’s &lt;em&gt;pathways project&lt;/em&gt; offers an amazing example of exploring book as interface that provokes probabilistic production in the reading process. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pathwaysproject.org/&quot;&gt;The Pathways Project&lt;/a&gt; explores the analogies between oral tradition (oAgora) and the internet (eAgora) in their shared challenge to the operations of print media (tAgora). The Pathways Project is full of insights and limits, both of which can provide useful launching places for our experiments here with book as interface.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;future of academic book
In her essay, Drucker makes some hints toward what we might find in emerging scholarly interpretive reading interfaces. There is a movement afoot that is gently and gradually trying to take seriously this call to imagine the academic book as interface in our emerging media landscape. The Future of the Academic Book project began as a collaborative project…Though I have had a hard time seeing how the FOAB project has interrupted the established dispositions of print and codex to allow the possibilities of emerging technologies, the community of discourse that has fostered this movement has most definitely demonstrated a desire for and commitment to a constructivist and collaborative process. Their patience and respect for tradition could create the necessary space for translation of the deeply ingrained material sensibilities embedded in the culture of the academic book. I hope to incorporate the innovative spirit and the patient wisdom of both Drucker and the FOAB project as we push toward imagining bible as interface.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have a model of book as interface that provokes probabilistic production in the practice of reading and some examples of design in this direction. In the next chapter, I will advocate for one particular affordance in our design of bible as interface, anarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2016 11:00:24 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/08/26/chapter-1-interface.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/08/26/chapter-1-interface.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>introduction - translating book</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Book is undergoing a major media transition as print wanes in its dominance and the internet and mobile devices transform our reading habits. With the ever entangled histories of bible and book, &lt;strong&gt;this emerging media age and its transformation of reading practices begs us to imagine bible as an anarchic interface, a space of contact where meaning is produced without the reign of an original&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of bible as an interface rather than simply as a container for content will allow us to explore the possibilities of emerging technologies to translate and transform enduring traditions of bible reading into the coming media age without succumbing to the temptations of typical media binaries of new and old, good and bad. As we consider the design of book interfaces that provoke probabilistic production in the practice of reading, I will advocate for attention to an affordance of anarchy that dethrones the governing role of a singular original without eradicating useful historical relations. Bible reading communities throughout history have provided some models for this anarchic interface and can provide important guidance and wisdom as we explore emerging media capacities for our relationship with books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on Johanna Drucker’s work with interface theory and the Humanities, I will begin with a look at interface as a way of interrupting the container notion of book and suggesting a greater focus on relationality and reading practices in our discussion of media transitions and reading interface design. Then, based on the philosophy of Emmanuel Levinas, I will argue for an anarchic relationality that ought to shape our interface design toward creative encounter that resists emerging media dispositions toward consumption. With the possibility and value of anarchic interface established, I will then suggest ways to pursue bible as anarchic interface in our emerging media age. A look back at the performance of anarchic interface on the Talmudic page and in illuminated medieval manuscripts will inform our both the theory and design of our interfaces. Finally, I will beckon us forward by offering two experiments that highlight the challenges and possibilities of anarchic interface design and will offer some possibilities in light of the pervasive anxiety about human relationship and reading practices in today’s media environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we get started into our exploration of interface, why even bother with these questions of bible, book, and technology?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;emergence-of-a-medium&quot;&gt;emergence of a medium&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the birth of the codex to the fall of the bible, medium has mattered in the life of bible both in its necessary entanglement with content and in its significant social effects. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.com/0197260616&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Birth of the Codex&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Roberts and Skeat give us a careful look at the storied material history of the technology that has come to dominate our cultural idea of book, the codex. Nearly half of the pages of their own codex are devoted to the role of early Christian practices of scripture in the rise of the codex to prominence as a book technology, with this bold claim emerging from their analysis of the manuscript data (p. 42):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/834a49a6-f358-49bc-aee9-9d3398d2fb9d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Acknowledging the difficulty of firmly establishing the ‘biblical’ category and signaling their sensitivity to the narrow provenance of manuscript evidence, all in Egypt, Roberts and Skeat still resoundingly suggest that bible as book begins exclusively as a papyrus codex. Newer manuscript evidence and different approaches to categories have challenged the ‘always’ of this conclusion. Yet, the strangeness of this early Christian preference for codex has been reinforced by many more recent explorations of this evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Give some examples…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a book that deeply shaped my own ideas about the adoption of codex technology by Christians, &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.com/0300069189&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Books and Readers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Harry Gamble focuses more on the readerly use of early Christian texts than on their literary production. Though he may differ in his conclusions from Roberts and Skeat, there is little doubt that bible played a part in the emergence of a new interface. Gamble suggests, “SOMETHING HERE ABOUT XIAN use and emergence of codex.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;add a note about other perspectives on role of bible in codex development - Gamble, Hurtado, etc. Offer p.oxy 1075 and nongbri article as an example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own work on the book as a technology for scripture in antiquity, I found a combination of Gamble, Epp, and O’Donnell provided a compelling picture of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twilight-of-an-icon&quot;&gt;twilight of an icon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first chapter of Timothy Beal’s book &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.com/0547737343&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Rise and Fall of the Bible&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is titled ‘The End of the Word as we Know It,’ and he feels fine (kindle location 371).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2244a689-1754-4a88-a5e1-55a0526693a4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cultural iconicity of ‘the Bible’ as ‘the Book of books’ that is undergoing deconstruction is the bible as authoritative, univocal, practical, accessible, comprehensive, and exclusive (Beal, &lt;em&gt;Rise and Fall&lt;/em&gt;, kindle location 121-122). As Beal also notes, it is not a coincidence that this transformation of the bible as cultural icon coincides with a major cultural translation of the book as a medium (&lt;em&gt;Rise and Fall&lt;/em&gt;, kindle location 1161).
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/5282aafe-b6bc-4a61-a18e-dd13d028db65.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Just as in antiquity, bible played a role in the emergence of a new book technology, so today, bible as book is entangled in a media transition from the reign of print to a proliferation of interfaces in our emerging media age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;medium-matters&quot;&gt;medium matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.com/0262631598&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Marshall McLuhan points us toward the cracks in the reign of print, that illustrious descendent of the codex, in the face of an emerging electronic age. McLuhan reminds us that technologies (media) are extensions of ourselves and that the message of every medium is its effect on our social relations (McLuhan, &lt;em&gt;Understanding Media&lt;/em&gt;, 7-8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/48f712c2-567d-45d7-8af0-2c504ad20c58.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Beyond the obvious and important entanglement of form and content, McLuhan emphasizes the impact of technologies on human relationship with the world and one another through a ‘change of scale’ not simply a newness of kind (McLuhan, &lt;em&gt;Understanding Media&lt;/em&gt;, 8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/840dc7ef-cb4a-40f6-b24d-b31f1deb6416.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Here, McLuhan challenges our binary tendencies between new and old and suggests that media emerge as a change in ‘existing processes’ that inevitably have social consequences. It is precisely this change in existing processes we find in the amplification of non-linear access from the emergence of the codex to the ubiquity of digital search. McLuhan suggests that the content of every ‘new’ medium is another existing medium (&lt;em&gt;Understanding Media&lt;/em&gt;, 8). Just as the codex performed the multiple columns per page of a scroll, so internet search performs and amplifies the print index. I refer to this phenomenon of media building upon and containing its predecessors as &lt;em&gt;material media translation&lt;/em&gt;. The language of translation is helpful here because it signals that all media transformations involve a negotiation between new and old with inevitable loss and gain. I use the phrase ‘material media’ to qualify this translation to differentiate this process from the common process of translation of texts into other forms of media such as sound and film. In material media translation, it is the materiality of the interface of the medium that is translated, not simply its ‘content,’ whatever that might entail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite material metaphor for this process of material media translation is a palimpsest, a manuscript that has been written on, erased, and then written on again. With each new medium writing over an existing medium (or many media) with only partial erasure, material media translation enacts a kind of palimpsest. Below is an image of a page from &lt;a href=&quot;http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b8470433r&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Codex Ephraemi Rescriptus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a fifth century manuscript of biblical texts in Greek, washed and written over in the 12th century with Greek translations of the fourth century Syriac writings of Ephrem the Syrian (the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Codex_Ephraemi_Rescriptus&quot;&gt;wikipedia entry on &lt;em&gt;Codex Ephraemi Rescriptus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is excellent and provides significant references for a deeper look at the manuscript). This beautiful material enactment of palimpsest, two column miniscule Greek translations of Syriac over single column uncial Greek biblical texts, illustrates marvelously the process of emerging media building upon exisuggest anything to us about the process of translation itself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/eb872868-9b10-4731-879e-b56785f62084.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Image of &lt;a href=&quot;http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b8470433r/f15.item&quot;&gt;Codex Ephraemi Rescriptus 1v (view 15)&lt;/a&gt; taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/us/FhPFH.i&quot;&gt;iOS app Gallica by Bibliothèque nationale de France&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of this process of material media translation as palimpsest, remembering bible’s rich media history will provide a helpful context and data for imagining how bible might be practiced as interface amidst the changing reading dispositions of our emerging media age. The material media translation of book from manuscript page to mobile screen already has and will continue to shape our reading practices. Focusing on book as interface, a space for encounter, will highlight the importance of the materiality of these interfaces in producing our reading practices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2016 08:11:11 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/08/26/introduction-translating-book.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/08/26/introduction-translating-book.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>space as thesis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that humanities research is undergoing a major media reimagining as the scholarly dominance of print wanes. In the last few years, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mla.org/About-Us/Governance/Committees/Committee-Listings/Professional-Issues/Committee-on-Information-Technology/Guidelines-for-Evaluating-Work-in-Digital-Humanities-and-Digital-Media&quot;&gt;Modern Language Association&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historians.org/teaching-and-learning/digital-history-resources/evaluation-of-digital-scholarship-in-history/guidelines-for-the-evaluation-of-digital-scholarship-in-history&quot;&gt;American Historical Association&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.collegeart.org/pdf/evaluating-digital-scholarship-in-art-and-architectural-history.pdf&quot;&gt;College Art Association/Society of Architechtural Historians&lt;/a&gt; have released guidelines for the evaluation of ‘digital’ scholarship for promotion and tenure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Digital’ can mean a lot of things, but in this case it has a simple function to identify academic work that is governed more by internet sensibilities than those of print. Relatedly, internet sensibilities could encompass a lot of different values, but here I use Internet sensibilities to signal a focus on process more than product, collaboration more than independent scholarly activity, and interface design as a critical part of content production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have worked on a dissertation that questions this media translation related to the communities of reading that constitute bible, I have struggled with how a project not governed by print sensibilities (comprehensive finished product, individual expertise, and content driven) might be evaluated. It seems that the currency of the dissertation is a clearly articulated thesis argued in a way that allows committee members to evaluate whether the thesis has been demonstrated as viable or not. I have &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2016/01/20/consuming-thesis.html&quot;&gt;reflected on thesis&lt;/a&gt; other places, so I will not bore us with a regurgitation of those questions. Yet, As his been a regular occurance with this project, some conversations with colleagues generated a question for me related to thesis and space. &lt;a href=&quot;http://ecoody.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;Elizabeth Coody&lt;/a&gt;, who works with countless writers in her role as director of the writing lab at Iliff, shared her notion of thesis as a promise a writer makes to an audience to set the limits of a relationship in a way. The relational framing of this promise struck me as significant, even though I still have many questions and concerns about the typical dominance of writerly intent in the conceptions of meaning making through reading. Is it possible that the limits of a particular space of dialog, with a regular rhythm of offerings to stimulate interaction and ongoing discussion, could constitute a promise kind of thesis? Let’s say, for example, I promised to offer annotated artifacts every other week for a year to facilitate dialog in this very space, bound by the limits of these interfaces. Could this commitment to a space and a regular process of inquiry operate as a thesis, even if the content of these offerings varied in focus and theme?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to demonstrate sustained and rigorous attention to the relationship between the design of interfaces, the curation and annotation of artifacts, and the facilitation of conversation within the space of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; could provide a placing (thesis) that foregrounds process over product, while the ongoing construction of the space itself could still offer a kind of tangible outcome for those who must evaluate. The promise here could be both a careful and sustained process along with a limited space/time for engagement, rather than a single content based argument articulated from beginning to end. Based on my pedagogical values of increased surface area, annotation of artifacts, and extending conversation, this thesis/space could be evaluated in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These criteria come from a longer entry I wrote, called &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2016/02/12/translating-thesis.html&quot;&gt;translating thesis&lt;/a&gt;, in response to my committee’s request for a thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does the technical design of the constellation of interfaces of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; shape and support the values articulated in the curation and conversation within the space? (e.g. Does an embedded comment engine or a search function that combines post and comments support the values of the space?). This criteria takes seriously the entanglement of form and content, medium and message. New media approaches have a tendency to over emphasize form and print projects can take form for granted and focus exclusively on content.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the design of the space responsive to user needs and audience feedback? (e.g. building translation from &lt;a href=&quot;postach.io&quot;&gt;postachio&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;quip.com&quot;&gt;quip&lt;/a&gt; for committee and adding zoomability and an email subscription option to the theme.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the smaller bits of writing and interaction provide useful surfaces for engagement and contact with the conversations of the space (increased surface area)? Is there an appropriate balance between connective tissue and fragments? (e.g. does the selection of a given artifact, such as a particular video clip, encourage more engagement or lead to unproductive confusion?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the curation and annotation of artifacts demonstrate careful attention to each artifact including suitable and substantial engagement with the theoretical conversation partners introduced? (e.g. I need more work to demonstrate the value of Benjamin’s &lt;em&gt;Arcades Project&lt;/em&gt; as a model for the value fragments and artifact annotation. I need to give more sustained attention to the relationship between revealing in Heidegger and anarchy in Levinas.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does the space encourage interaction that extends the conversation toward greater attention to the nuance of an artifact and the ideas it generates through struggling with language, asking new questions, and sharing related artifacts?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the sustained processes of design, curation, annotation, and conversation offer suggestions for ways in which bible might be performed in a media culture not dominated by print? Does the ongoing and collaborative construction of a space like &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; encourage a set of dispositions that can challenge the perceived tendencies of internet media toward shallowness and distraction?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the writing throughout the space of high quality, combining both accessibility and artistry? Are the exchanges between community members respectful and constructive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these criteria are specific to my particular project and these suggestions for evaluation principles are only a place to begin. Could this list be generalized in ways to be useful for others? Perhaps there are other criteria that would be fitting for a project like this or ways to clarify the values and mechanisms of these articulated principles? With a set of agreed upon evaluation metrics, could this notion of a sustained and careful attention to the construction of a space function as a thesis? Could these criteria for evaluation offer us a place to begin imagining structures that would support different kinds of dissertations, with various modes of scholarship to offer the academy? Could this list be augmented, translated, and adjusted to fit the needs of several different promises between student and committee? Are others using criteria for evaluation that have proven useful for negotiating dissertation projects that do not conform to the typical processes of print production? Could criteria like these be used to evaluate even print dissertations, since print is simply another means of constructing space?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 22:13:43 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/05/14/space-as-thesis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/05/14/space-as-thesis.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>interfacing religion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In light of the prevalent anxiety and curiosity about both human relationship and reading practices online, I have two simple claims, that meaningful human encounter is possible online and that bible offers an interface for this encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;See this dropmark collection, &lt;a href=&quot;http://drp.mk/QNNV1WTYBG&quot;&gt;Relating and Reading Online&lt;/a&gt; for a collection of links to current examples of the anxiety and curiosity regarding human relationship and reading online (e.g. Nicholas Carr, Sherry Turkle, and the Future of the Academic Book). This dropmark collection is an experiment in a media translation of footnote. I can continue to collect related items from the web and have them aggregate here. I can even invite collaborators and add discussions to the collection. I initially tried to embed this collection in the page, but the size of the embed was out of proportion to the role of the collection in the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may seem like these two claims have little to do with one another, other than the role of the internet in online human encounter and in reading practices these days. Yet, building on a Levinasian articulation of bible as the book of books, I will argue that reading practices produced by bible signal the very possibility of meaningful human encounter and provide a framework for imagining interpretive reading communities performed in emerging media spaces. Let us begin with the Book of books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in his career, Emmanuel Levinas sat for some interviews with Philippe Nemo and the transcripts of these interviews were transcribed and translated by Richard A. Cohen into a marvelous little volume titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/0820701785&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is no surprise to me that the compelling nature of &lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt; takes the form of a series of conversations rather than a written philosophical treatise. These conversations are not theses argued carefully and comprehensively, but points of encounter with the ideas of a man that beg us to explore more. Though the irony of my secondary reflections on these now written transcripts is not lost on me, this conversational model does &lt;em&gt;speak&lt;/em&gt; to the intimate role of speech in the relation with the other for Levinas. In the introduction to ‘Is Ontology Fundamental?’ in &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/0253210798&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Emmanuel Levinas: Basic Philosophical Writings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Simon Critchley nicely highlights the possibilities human speech offers for an encounter with the other that is not governed by comprehension:
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/8935293b-6098-4f15-8b78-e4b633d585b7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Critchley, &lt;em&gt;BPW&lt;/em&gt;, 1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transcripts of these interviews were my introduction to the ideas, thought, and methodology of Levinas and as I continue to encounter more of his work, I come back to these interviews and hear them with deeper resonance and richness each time. If anyone were to question why a bible project like &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; would be so interested in a continental philosopher such as Levinas, even a cursory glance at these interviews would clarify. In the first question of the first interview transcribed in &lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;, which is titled ‘Bible and Philosophy,’ Levinas connects thinking to reading books as a ‘modality’ of humanness and suggests that for him, the Bible is ‘the book par excellence’ (Cohen translating Levinas, &lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;, 22). The conversation continues toward questions about the relationship between bible, philosophical writings and the Russian literary classics. At one point, Nemo asks Levinas about the ways he has ‘harmonized’ biblical and philosophical thinking, to which Levinas responds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/f5c0ab72-fa5e-41da-9faf-ea1283a6cf86.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Cohen translating Levinas, &lt;em&gt;EI&lt;/em&gt;, 23)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A close read of this response could take us on a journey through much of Levinas’s philosophical ideas, but we will focus on just a few echoes. What we will find is that bible and the process of reading it encourages, provides an interface with religion, thus with the face of the other. The bookishness he mentions in his initial response to Nemo about where thinking begins now gets wrapped into what Levinas calls ‘the religious sentiment.’ We have to remember here that Levinas often uses words in ways that are unfamiliar. Curiously, I have been working with this passage for several years and it wasn’t until just recently that the role of religion gained amplitude. My contentious background as an evangelically trained biblical exegete always drew me toward his correlation of mystery, possibility, exegesis, and transcendence in the underlined section above. I hadn’t even taken the time to consider this response as an articulation of Levinas’s theory of religion, or at least a statement about the practices that stimulated his religious imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For a fuller exploration of the operations of religion in Levinas’s thought, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books/about/Emmanuel_Levinas_Levinas_and_the_questio.html?id=xHYKc4PVUBAC&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Emmanuel Levinas: Levinas and the Question of Religion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Here is a quote from p. 3 of the Introduction.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/b36db1f8-50b6-4190-8c42-16bd9941be70.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Levinas is careful to offer several clarifications about what he means by religious sentiment and its relationship to books. He is particularly keen to emphasize that this is not some literary minimization of the religious, but a recognition of the ‘sacredness’ of the process of reading. A relationship with books, and particularly bible, not a set of determinate beliefs, constitutes this religious sentiment for Levinas.
As I have noted &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2014/08/31/whats-in-a-title.html&quot;&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, I often use anarthrous lower case bible instead of ‘the Bible’ to signal the vast cultural phenomena of bible beyond a single book. Perhaps Torah, written and oral, is a more familiar identifier for the interpretive phenomenon Levinas describes here. See note 8 on page 70 of &lt;em&gt;Levinas and the Question of Religion&lt;/em&gt; for a list of resources on Levinas’s reflections on Torah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending so much of my time thinking about the role of book technologies in religious identity, I have often missed the importance of the ’&lt;em&gt;relationship with&lt;/em&gt; books’ in this discussion of bible. If we follow this passage further, we find this &lt;em&gt;relationship&lt;/em&gt; with books restated in the commentators, the hermeneutic glimpsing, and the place of interpretation. It is not bible as a recipe book for determinate beliefs that signaled transcendence, rather the possibilities found in its infinite process of reading as meaning making. This process of reading as meaning, interpretation, Levinas suggests bible and philosophy may have in common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This connection of religion to a relationship with books, most particularly with bible, provides the backdrop for the role of bible in facilitating meaningful human encounter. A look at a few other places where religion shows up in the writings and thought of Levinas will help illustrate this connection. In an essay from 1951 titled ‘Is Ontology Fundamental?,’ we find Levinas suggesting that metaphysics (or thinking in general) may not have the first word on human meaning, or relation with the other, which we also hear in &lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;, 24-25. In ‘Is Ontology Fundamental?,’ Levinas applies this questioning of metaphysics to Heidegger’s ontology and the necessary comprehension at its core (&lt;em&gt;BPW&lt;/em&gt;, 1-2). As the question mark in the title suggests, this essay asks if there is something more fundamental than or anterior to ontology, which, in the end, collapses back into comprehension (&lt;em&gt;BPW&lt;/em&gt;, 5). Levinas offers a response to this question in a move from knowledge (horizon of being) to speech (language) as fundamental in the relation with the other. This relation with the other that exceeds comprehension, and thus is not founded on ontology, Levinas calls &lt;em&gt;religion&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;BPW&lt;/em&gt;, 7-8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/ff45ef65-358a-4acb-a90e-fae4eb2b7efa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Critchley, Atterton, and Graham translating Levinas, &lt;em&gt;Emmanuel Levinas: Basic Philosophical Writings&lt;/em&gt;, 7)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levinas goes on to write, ‘Religion is the relation with a being as a being,’ thus not governed by knowledge of being (&lt;em&gt;BPW&lt;/em&gt;, 8-9). Does this relation, this encounter, with the other, that exceeds and precedes knowledge, have some connection to the ‘relationship with books’ we heard in the passage above from &lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;, since both are spoken of in religious language? We will return to this question in a moment. Levinas moves from religion to a discussion of face in ‘Is Ontology Fundamental?,’ using similar language for both. We hear an echo of ’Religion is &lt;em&gt;the relation with a being as a being&lt;/em&gt;’ in his suggestion that ’The relation with the face, speech, as event of collectivity, &lt;em&gt;is a relation with beings as such&lt;/em&gt;, as pure beings’ (&lt;em&gt;BPW&lt;/em&gt;, 10, emphasis my own). If we follow this overlap in language, the relation with the face is religion. We hear this connection of religion and face even more poignantly in his later work, &lt;em&gt;Totality and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;, where Levinas continues his questioning of ontology and calls religion an &lt;em&gt;ultimate structure&lt;/em&gt; and the face to face an &lt;em&gt;ultimate situation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/c78ce490-365d-4d91-a30e-ee089497024f.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Lingis translating Levinas, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/0820702455&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Totality and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 80)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion and the face are undoubtedly connected for Levinas and this encounter with the face of the other, which is religion (that which is irreducible to comprehension), is somehow signaled by the mysterious possibilities of exegesis of the Bible. Yet, Levinas is clear that the face is that which makes a being human, not a thing (&lt;em&gt;BPW&lt;/em&gt;, 8-9), so in this sense, bible is not a face. He speaks of reading as a ‘modality of being,’ not being itself (&lt;em&gt;EI&lt;/em&gt;, 22). So, the interpretive practices of bible, the mysterious possibilities of exegesis in each character encountered (both alphabetic and narrative) offer not a face but an inter&lt;em&gt;face&lt;/em&gt; with religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interface is this space of ‘relationship with.’ It is the relationship with books, the discourse of reading, that constitutes the religious sentiment for Levinas, not only the books themselves. In her essay, ‘Humanities Approaches to Interface Theory,’ Johanna Drucker helpfully intertwines digital media studies explorations of interface design with humanities questions of subjectivity. She gives us a view of interface as more of a theatre than a window (Drucker, ’&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.culturemachine.net/index.php/cm/issue/view/23&quot;&gt;Interface Theory&lt;/a&gt;’, 9).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/6e6a0bf2-9efe-4eec-97a8-ed4c587cce3e.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
(Drucker, ‘Interface Theory,’ 9)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;’Interface is &lt;em&gt;what we read&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;how we read&lt;/em&gt; combined through engagement.’ Before I had encountered Drucker’s work, this question of the relationship between how we read and what we read drove my desire to explore bible &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; media (see &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2014/08/31/whats-in-a-title.html&quot;&gt;what’s in a title?&lt;/a&gt; for more). In this performative notion of interface, I hear many resonances with the religious sentiment as a relationship with books in Levinas. Much like relation with the face–religion–grounds the possibility for knowledge, here, Drucker suggests that ‘Interface is a provocation to cognitive experience,’ not its consequence (Drucker, ‘Interface Theory,’ 9).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, bible is a religious mode insofar as it provides an interface for encounter (engagement) that opens to human meaning which is not at first governed by comprehension, but provides the conditions of possibility for knowledge itself. Now that we have seen how bible as book, an interface, can shape the possibilities for human meaning and meaningful humanness, I will turn to a closer look at Drucker’s interface theory and its relationship to subjectivity and the face in Levinas. This relationship between face and interface will lead us to explore two important ideas in Levinas, proximity and infinity, while providing some guidelines for interface design that could translate this religious sentiment of bible as book into our emerging media ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2016 16:01:26 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/04/29/interfacing-religion.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/04/29/interfacing-religion.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>a proximate thesis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Building on the experiments that have guided this space of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; thus far and listening to the counsel of my committee, the remainder of this project will argue that &lt;strong&gt;the infinity and anarchy at work in the proximity of the face in Emmanuel Levinas’s writings suggest a difficult materiality that can offer bible an afterlife beyond print as new media interface&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My use of ‘difficult materiality’ here is an extension of Levinas’s notion of ‘difficult freedom.’ His collection of essays by this name, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/080185783X&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Difficult Freedom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, translated by Seán Hand, begins with an epigraph that quietly signals the role of materiality and bible in his thinking. The epigraph reads, ‘Freedom on tablets of stone (Tractate of Principles 6.2).’
Pursuing a media ‘afterlife’ for bible is a direct invocation of Walter Benjamin’s essay, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ricorso.net/rx/library/criticism/guest/Benjamin_W/Benjamin_W1.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Task of the Translator&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, translated by Harry Zohn. The anarchic and palimpsestuous notion of afterlife in Benjamin’s discussion of translation (see &lt;em&gt;Task&lt;/em&gt;, p. 71) shapes my own approach to media translation in this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his understanding of bible as book, Levinas already offers a model for meaning that takes seriously the material encounter of reading as a bounded opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/5cb997fc-3840-4c45-8f6d-57d0eb814c35.png&quot; width=&quot;2853&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Richard A. Cohen translating Emmanuel Levinas, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/0820701785&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 23)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working from this passage in &lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt; and its contact points with other places in Levinas’s writings, I will demonstrate the possibility of translating this bounded openness of bible as book, ‘that extraordinary presence of its characters, that ethical plenitude and its mysterious possibilities of exegesis, which originally signaled trascendence,’ into an emerging media interface (see &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2015/06/07/reading-interfaces.html&quot;&gt;reading interfaces&lt;/a&gt; for some preliminary reflections on this). I will begin with a close look at the notion of proximity as a materiality in Levinas’s exposition of the face to face encounter. Based on this difficult materiality of proximity, I will suggest a materiality for online spaces that challenges the common distinction between face-to-face and online (the seeds of this conversation can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2015/03/21/proliferation-of-faces.html&quot;&gt;proliferation of faces&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2015/11/01/reclaiming-face-to-face-in-a-digital-era.html&quot;&gt;reclaiming the face to face in a digital era&lt;/a&gt;). With these philosophical underpinnings, I will then offer design principles and sketches toward bible as interface that translates the religious sentiment of bible as book into our emerging media age (&lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2015/03/24/mediating-proximity.html&quot;&gt;mediating proximity&lt;/a&gt; offers hints in this direction).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2016 09:25:07 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/04/09/a-proximate-thesis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/04/09/a-proximate-thesis.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>translating thesis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Through some difficult and useful conversations with my committee, I have come to some greater clarity on what I wanted from this &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; project. The hypothesis governing my work here has been that sustained and careful attention to the ongoing production of a space built on the pedagogical values of increased surface area, annotation of artifacts, and extending conversation can offer a different and legitimate medium (what I call a material media translation) for dissertation and for bible as the cultural dominance of print wanes. The process of producing the space of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;, with the consistent entanglement of form and content (medium and message) provide the thesis for this dissertation as a whole, a nucleus, and a placing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whole, nucleus, and placing are all ways my committee and I have talked about the role of thesis in academic work. Though my rhetoric can, at times, suggest an anxiety about print, I do not intend to argue for the eradication of print modalities, simply the possibility for meaningful alternatives in different media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demonstrating sustained and rigorous attention to the relationship between the design of the interfaces, the curation and annotation of artifacts, and the facilitation of conversation within the space of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; can provide a placing (thesis) that foregrounds process over product, though the ongoing construction of the space itself can offer a kind of tangible outcome. Based on my stated values of increased surface area, annotation of artifacts, and extending conversation, this thesis/space can be evaluated in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Does the technical design of the constellation of interfaces of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; shape and support the values articulated in the curation and conversation within the space? (e.g. Does an embedded comment engine or a search function that combines post and comments support the values of the space?). This criteria takes seriously the entanglement of form and content, medium and message. New media approaches have a tendency to over emphasize form and print projects can take form for granted and focus exclusively on content.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is the design of the space responsive to user needs and audience feedback? (e.g. building translation from postach.io to quip for committee and adding zoomability and an email subscription option to the theme.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do the smaller bits of writing and interaction provide useful surfaces for engagement and contact with the conversations of the space (increased surface area)? Is there an appropriate balance between connective tissue and fragments? (e.g. does the selection of a given artifact, such as a particular video clip, encourage more engagement or lead to unproductive confusion?)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do the curation and annotation of artifacts demonstrate careful attention to each artifact including suitable and substantial engagement with the theoretical conversation partners introduced? (e.g. I need more work to demonstrate the value of Benjamin’s &lt;em&gt;Arcades Project&lt;/em&gt; as a model for the value fragments and artifact annotation. I need to give more sustained attention to the relationship between revealing in Heidegger and anarchy in Levinas.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Does the space encourage interaction that extends the conversation toward greater attention to the nuance of an artifact and the ideas it generates through struggling with language, asking new questions, and sharing related artifacts?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do the sustained processes of design, curation, annotation, and conversation offer suggestions for ways in which bible might be performed in a media culture not dominated by print? Does the ongoing and collaborative construction of a space like &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; encourage a set of dispositions that can challenge the perceived tendencies of internet media toward shallowness and distraction?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is the writing throughout the space of high quality, combining both accessibility and artistry?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These suggestions for evaluation principles are only a place to begin. Perhaps there are other criteria that would be fitting for a project like this or ways to clarify the values and mechanisms of these articulated principles? With a set of agreed upon evaluation metrics, could this notion of a sustained and careful attention to the construction of a space function as a thesis?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am well aware that this suggestion of space as thesis may not be viable or may need more theoretical work to translate in ways that make sense as a doctoral dissertation. In light of this potential impossibility and to signal my respect for our disciplinary traditions, I have composed a draft of a more traditionally structured dissertation with a thesis statement and chapters outlining the argument. Though this proposal does not intend in any way to fold in all of the work done thus far on &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;, it constitutes a continuation of this project with a different trajectory. I look forward to the conversations that will shape whatever project we decide to work on together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;thesis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connecting emerging digital reading technologies to the non-linear access afforded by the codex and to the atomization of rabbinic readings of Torah can offer bible an afterlife beyond print as an anarchic interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;remediating bible?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/949c3a55-3d21-45e1-95f8-261f7222d7ca.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Timothy Beal, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/B004KABBYK&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Rise and Fall of the Bible&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, kindle location 2642)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will set the stage with Tim Beal’s &lt;em&gt;Rise and Fall of the Bible&lt;/em&gt;, which asks if the twilight of print might signal the end of bible as a book. How might the cultural phenomenon of bible be performed as the dominance of print wanes? Focusing on one particular technological innovation, non-linear access, and its relationship to one specific reading strategy, atomization, will offer insights into how emerging media interface design can keep bible connected to its ancient reading traditions, while translating these traditions and practices into a new medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;translating non-linear access&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/fd4a12a6-8630-4e13-bcb9-77168d1c6c9b.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(James O’Donnell, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/067400194X&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avatars of the Word&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 54)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning with James O’Donnell’s &lt;em&gt;Avatars of the Word&lt;/em&gt;, trace the material media translation of non-linear access from the invention of the codex to the reference systems of early manuscripts to print indexes to digital search. Connecting search to this ancient tradition of non-linear access can help contextualize some of the anxiety around the atomization tendencies of new media search practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;difficult atomization&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/3f03efb2-ae6e-459f-bc27-ec4586dd4c23.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Michael L. Satlow, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/0231134894&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Creating Judaism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 127)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explore ancient rabbinic Torah reading practices as a different form of atomization that could provide some translatable dispositions to ground the fragmentary reading practices of the internet. Focus on the mechanisms of rabbinic midrash as a difficult atomization, bound to the tradition while infinitely opening to meaning through sustained attention to and interruptive conversation around small fragments of biblical text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;proximate interface&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/19596c93-d78d-42e3-a309-7247e9c928c2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Emmanuel Levinas, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/0820701785&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ethics and Infinity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 23)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This difficult atomization of rabbinic discourse modeled for Emmanuel Levinas a humanness bound to the other in the face as proximity, a contact without grasp. Use some examples from Levinas’s reflections on rabbinic reading to connect difficult atomization to the operations of proximity in his philosophy of the face. Explore how the proximity of the face to face encounter could provide a framework for new media interfaces that encourage a difficult atomization, where anarchic fragments demand engagement and interrupt content consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;bible as medium: *proxinity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Return to Tim Beal’s Italy lectures and move from tracing the media of the bible to the possibility of bible &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; medium. I will sketch a prototype design for bible as anarchic interface, outlining how each design element performs (or fails to perform) a proximity of atomization that maintains the tension between the ancient reading traditions of bible and its ongoing media translations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 06:58:40 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/02/12/translating-thesis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/02/12/translating-thesis.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>consuming thesis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that the idea of thesis makes me uncomfortable. Recently, I have been asked to offer a clearer articulation (thesis) of what I am trying to say about the relationship between Emmanuel Levinas’s philosophy of the face and technologies of reading and writing. After reading back over the conversations of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;, particularly the hints toward these ideas in &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2015/03/21/proliferation-of-faces.html&quot;&gt;proliferation of faces&lt;/a&gt;, below are the telescoping theses I came up with. Each of these statements can be taken on their own or together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Medium matters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The face to face describes a material encounter. This inter&lt;em&gt;face&lt;/em&gt; is not limited to the material medium of human perception.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inter&lt;em&gt;faces&lt;/em&gt; (technologies) shape meaning as much as the ‘texts’ they perform. The face to face in Levinas begs for a humanness that resists consumption, a contact without grasp (proximity). Reading and writing interfaces built on emerging internet media technologies can encourage dispositions toward non-commodified human encounter, i.e. the face to face.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rabbinic readings of bible as book first signaled for Levinas a meaning making beyond cognitive categorization (consumption). As the cultural dominance of print wanes, material media translations of bible (and book) from bound print codex to dynamic aggregation of digital fragments can provide spaces to practice the ongoing entanglement of strategies and tactics that constitute the cultural phenomenon of bible as a human interface.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up spending a lot of time considering this question of thesis and trying to concisely distill, condense, crystalize, dare I say commodify, what I am trying to say in this dissertation. Whatever I come up with here is partial and flawed and, at its best, open and curious. So, I keep wondering, what work is this process of ‘thesis distilling’ doing for me or for my readers? Is this process useful for me as a writer or is it more of a courteous consideration for the reader, so that the aim (payoff?) of a work is always in view? Does thesis offer a particular genre or guild specific strategy of discourse that can offer an interface for engagement or evaluation? Is a singular and clearly articulated thesis the defining mark of the dissertation genre, a decidedly print governed genre? If so, is there a way to translate the work that thesis-izing does into a less print dominated medium?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My initial title for this post was ‘thesis-izing’. It turns out this word ‘thesisize’ has an entry in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Thesisize&quot;&gt;urban dictionary&lt;/a&gt; and has a hashtag presence on twitter (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/thesisizing&quot;&gt;#thesisizing&lt;/a&gt;). Different than the process of distilling and consolidating I am struggling with here, thesis-ize is more often used to indicate the arduous task of composing the large academic work typically governed by this singular and clearly articulated thesis. It is suggestive that this distilled nugget of a thesis, the most consumable interface of a work, has become a synecdoche for the entire creative process that marks the largest project of many students’ academic careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had to articulate a thesis for this particular post on thesis, it would be what was just suggested in the note above, that &lt;em&gt;a thesis is the most consumable or commodified interface of a creative work&lt;/em&gt;. Given that &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; is exploring reading/writing interfaces that resist the dominance of commodification, can we translate the values of thesis into a medium that is more fragmentary, dynamic, and aggregative? Or not? Let’s imagine thesis undergoing something like the Lyotardian move from university to institute, from metanarrative to &lt;em&gt;petit récit&lt;/em&gt; or ‘little narrative’ (Lyotard, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/0816611734&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Postmodern Condition&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 60)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/e5c54775-829c-48f9-9b3a-8e296e76b0d4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the space of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;, a single overarching narrative (thesis) does not govern the conversation. Instead, theses of the ‘little narrative’ variety &lt;strong&gt;emerge&lt;/strong&gt; through use, the ongoing and palimpsestuous struggle of curation and interaction. If we take this Lyotardian notion of little narrative alongside the literary montage methodology of Walter Benjamin’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/0674008022&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arcades Project&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/f5188650-0edf-49fe-811c-12ab8198cd16.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we can begin to imagine an &lt;em&gt;an-archic&lt;/em&gt; performance of thesis (see &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2015/01/11/anarchic-approximations.html&quot;&gt;anarchic approximations&lt;/a&gt; for specifics on my use of the term ‘anarchic’). Instead of an originary idea reigning over a work, that then comes to represent the work in its totality, theses can arise in the interfaces that shape the space of a work as it is used. I make claims all over these spaces, as do others, so in one sense, theses abound (or are they unbound?). Yet, this online medium, built from a constellation of interfaces, attempts to practice a translation of thesis from the consumable &lt;em&gt;arche&lt;/em&gt; of metanarrative to the poeitic fragments of everyday practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In his reflections on Lyotard’s later writings, Stephen Barker suggests an explicit connection between fragment and &lt;em&gt;petit récit&lt;/em&gt; in Lyotard (Barker, &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=qEaNwpOsonwC&amp;amp;pg=PT90&amp;amp;dq=lyotard+petit+recit+fragment&amp;amp;source=gbs_toc_r&amp;amp;cad=3#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=lyotard petit recit fragment&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;“The Weight of Writing: Lyotard’s Anti-Aesthetic in ‘À l’écrit bâté’”&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/1e8ca823-dd37-4b4f-9ee9-86df029646a9.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 12:55:23 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/01/20/consuming-thesis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/01/20/consuming-thesis.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>mapping interfaces</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At a recent Society of Biblical Literature conference session in Atlanta, my friend Tim talked about our present age in terms of a proliferation of media. This term, ‘proliferation,’ struck me as a wonderful expression of creativity and emergence. At a simplistic level, all I mean here by proliferation is a rapid expansion. Yet, this process of expansion carries a notion of explosion and dissemination at a rate that makes it impossible to keep up with traditional demands for classification and categorization. In the first few paragraphs of Bennington and Massumi’s English translation of Lyotard’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/0816611734&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Postmodern Condition&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we find mention of proliferation and technologies (p. 4):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/da16759b-3622-41de-bb45-b9e825f107db.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though Marshall McLuhan doesn’t use the term ‘proliferation’ explicitly in either &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/144261269X&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gutenberg Galaxy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/1584230738&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Understanding Media&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Taylor and Harris note in &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/0335218113&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Critical Theories of Mass Media: Then and Now&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that ‘a proliferation of new media’ threatening the dominance of print sits right at the junction between these two major works of McLuhan’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/99b1a400-757e-40e1-8001-39b67bab312e.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifty years later, I am still working with the cultural ramifications of ‘the point at which the lineal-visual hegemony of print technology begins to unravel in the &lt;strong&gt;face&lt;/strong&gt; of a &lt;em&gt;proliferation&lt;/em&gt; of new media’ (Taylor and Harris, &lt;em&gt;Critical Theories of Mass Media&lt;/em&gt;, 92, emphasis added). Taylor and Harris also note the ways in which McLuhan’s writing in &lt;em&gt;Understanding Media&lt;/em&gt; attempts to perform the characteristics of the new media he explores, eschewing what they call a ‘scholarly &lt;em&gt;proliferation&lt;/em&gt; of detail and citation.’ This is precisely the approach I have taken in the material media that make up &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;. In fact, in one of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://aproximatebible.postach.io/post/mapping-interfaces#comment-2464887834&quot;&gt;comments on this post&lt;/a&gt;, my friend and colleague Gil Rosenberg described the proliferation of media in this project wonderfully, saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2ec5e88c-74a2-4c86-a91d-4a7675ab0b13.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can feel the threat that this proliferation of media might pose to an academy and a biblical society that have constructed an identity out of the desire and acumen for consolidation toward an original thesis, comprehensive encyclopedias, and the pursuit of an original manuscript. Perhaps we can find some ways to translate these demands for consolidation into the constantly emerging landscape that is this particular new media age?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; project is far from a proliferation on the scale of google or facebook, but there are several possible interfaces with the conversations and communities that compose this work and even more tools involved in the facilitation of these interfaces. Below, I will try to provide a map, or some maps, to encourage exploration. This Prezi offers a graphical and spatial map of the interfaces and tools that shape the landscape of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This map is a snapshot in time of the landscape, which may change and evolve as new tools become available and needed. I chose Prezi as a mapping tool here because it illustrates a balance of the pathfinding and the exploration possible in new media translations of maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;composing-for-web-not-print-postachio-and-evernote&quot;&gt;composing for web, not print (postach.io and Evernote)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary interface with &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; for most people will be the web space &lt;a href=&quot;http://aproximatebible.postach.io&quot;&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/a&gt;. The team at &lt;a href=&quot;http://postach.io&quot;&gt;postach.io&lt;/a&gt; has provided a wonderful public web interface for those of us who love to write and compose in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evernote.com&quot;&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt;. I have used Evernote for years as an artifact and note aggregator across devices. The mobile sensibilities of Evernote and the sparse formatting demands were what initially drew me to the tool. As I have continued to use Evernote, the interplay of fragment, collection, and search in the interface has become a material media translation for me of the literary montage methodology in Walter Benjamin’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/0674008022&quot;&gt;Arcades Project&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/4010a1db-377e-4eb5-8be3-95f6316136a1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have linked an Evernote notebook to &lt;a href=&quot;http://aproximatebible.postach.io&quot;&gt;aproximatebible.postach.io&lt;/a&gt; through pistach.io’s core Evernote integration. So, anytime I add the tag ‘published’ to a note in this notebook, the Evernote sync process triggers a translation of this note into a web page on the &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have written about my discomfort with this ‘published’ tag convention in &lt;a href=&quot;http://amemorablefancy.postach.io/post/published&quot;&gt;Published?&lt;/a&gt;. Early versions of this integration allowed users to choose their own tag to signal postach.io to translate a note to the web space. If I could choose a tag now, I would use “translate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I am composing for a web medium and not print, I compose posts with &lt;a href=&quot;https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;markdown&lt;/a&gt;, a basic syntax for formatting text that is easy to read and can be readily translated into HTML. This Evernote - postach.io integration enacts a material media translation of my curated posts from Evernote markdown to HTML in a themed web space. Though my Evernote notebook is private, all changes I make to any posts tagged as published are translated to the public web space on postach.io the next time Evernote syncs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the course of writing this, I realized that it would be meaningful to indicate both a release date for each post and its most recent update date. I have changed the curated by date in post headings to be the created date from Evernote and I added a most recent update date in parentheses. The curated date indicates when the note was first created in Evernote, not when it was first translated to postach.io.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-conversation-disqus-and-quip&quot;&gt;making conversation (disqus and Quip)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most significant interface for &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; has been the integration of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/home/forums/aproximatebible/&quot;&gt;disqus&lt;/a&gt; conversation engine into the postach.io space. One of the main reasons I chose a web based medium for this project, rather than print, was to explore the asynchronous conversation and engagement possibilities with my intellectual community, both internal to the project and beyond. Disqus provides a widely used online discussion framework that is designed to integrate well with other web tools and spaces. The postach.io - disqus integration embeds a conversation space at the bottom of each post, with a disqus thread dedicated to each &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; entry. In this disqus space, people can engage and interact with me, the project, and with each other through questions and comments and sharing resources. The questions and ideas offered in this discussion become a part of the space that is the post and thus, they become a part of the project. Disqus offers a public and participatory interface for &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; and has proven a wonderfully rich space for engagement and encounter, thanks mostly to my generous, curious and creative intellectual community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting design note regarding this disqus integration is the decision to locate these discussion threads at the bottom of the page. This is a widely used format for discussion on web artifacts in many other tools (e.g. blogs, news sites, etc.) and it facilitates an ease of technological integration. Yet, we can see the palimpsestuous echoes of print footnotes in this interface design. At the bottom of the page, after the ‘body’ of the work, we find the indications of our conversation partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t decide if these ‘footer’ conversation spaces are a media translation of footnotes or endnotes, or a mashup of the two? Footnotes, as a print interface, are dictated by the material size of a print page, whereas endnotes are shaped by the transitions in or completion of a particular content unit. Since we still call these web reading interfaces, ‘pages,’ (a cultural palimpsest of its own) it isn’t hard to imagine the spaces and interactions at the bottom of the page as under foot. Yet, the material limits of a web page do not dictate the footer interface as the page dimensions do in print. Undoubtedly, there are material limits to the design and shape of a web page, but most often, it is a transition in a content unit (e.g. the end of my writing in a post) that signals the foot of the page on the web. Further, the larger project of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; has several ‘pages’ of content with notes and conversation at the bottom of each page, not simply at the end of the project, wherever that may be. Perhaps, these footer disqus conversations are most like a translation of chapter endnotes in a print codex. All that said, I look forward to digital dissertation projects that use technologies translating manuscript marginalia more than print footnotes, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/about/about-medium-9eac453da935#.s6s2ewe5r&quot;&gt;medium&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://lit.genius.com&quot;&gt;genius&lt;/a&gt;. Medium brings us one of the most inspiring new ways of imagining collaborative reading interface beyond print.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2014/11/24/notes-afoot.html&quot;&gt;notes afoot&lt;/a&gt; for more of my reflections on footnotes as an interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial hope was to have this disqus space provide a place for my dissertation committee to regularly participate in the project by critically engaging my curation and writing, while also contributing to the community dialog that ensued. Many factors, including the publicness of this space and the unfamiliar timeline of participating in smaller bits along the way, have limited my engagement with my committee in the postach.io/disqus interface of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a way to practice a kind of material media translation and to create a more familiar and private interface for my committee and me to have conversation around the quality and content of the project, I built a small python application to translate postach.io posts into Quip documents. &lt;a href=&quot;https://quip.com&quot;&gt;Quip&lt;/a&gt; is a mobile-centric collaborative authoring tool that allows invited accounts to co-author documents and have conversations in the margins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ll be releasing a post soon that goes into more detail about this translation application and what it has taught me about material media translation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quip offers another interface for &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;, but a private one in this case. Comments, conversations, and changes my committee and I make in Quip do not automatically sync to Evernote or postach.io, so they are only available to the four of us. Yet, I have no doubt that the things I discuss with my committee in Quip will lead to revisions, additions, and new conversations in the postach.io interface. With the addition of Quip, we can now see that each entry I compose in this dissertation has a minimum of three material versions (Evernote, postach.io, and Quip), each constructing a different reading interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the advantages of Quip over the disqus interface, related to my reflections above on footnotes, is Quip’s marginalia model of comments and conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-space-github-and-python&quot;&gt;making space (GitHub and Python)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crafting the material spaces of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; has as much to do with the meaning of this project as does the content of the conversation. Medium matters. As I have highlighted &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2015/06/07/reading-interfaces.html&quot;&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, postach.io offers an integration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/about&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; that allows me to customize the interface of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; to fit the theoretical reflections of this project and the needs of my reading community. &lt;a href=&quot;https://git-scm.com&quot;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; is a revision control system that allows developers to write code collaboratively, to test and discuss code before making it live, and to track changes and history throughout the project life cycle. GitHub is one of many hosting services for git projects that makes it easy to collaborate and share code with people all over the world. Git is the primary tool I use to make and track changes to &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; interfaces, but GitHub offers a public interface for this code and the history of my changes. I began with a copy of an existing postach.io theme called gridley and built from there. You can see this code and its history in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/textpotential/theme-gridly&quot;&gt;GitHub repository for this site theme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also be using GitHub to provide a public interface for the python modules I build to manage the posatch.io to Quip translation and the &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2015/03/24/mediating-proximity.html&quot;&gt;proxinity&lt;/a&gt; bible interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;translating-bibliography-twitter-and-zotero&quot;&gt;translating bibliography (Twitter and Zotero)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I discuss in my reflections on bibliography in &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible/2014/10/12/curating-the-conversation.html&quot;&gt;curating the conversation&lt;/a&gt;, there are two main interfaces for resource aggregation beyond the linking done within the entries in &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org&quot;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; is an open source bibliographic management tool that allows me to collect and organize artifacts (books, articles, web pages, links, etc.) related to this project. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/textualpotential/items/tag/aproximatebible&quot;&gt;Zotero collection for &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is publicly available for browsing and searching, but I have retained the exclusive rights to add to the collection. Though the tool can do more, my use of this Zotero public interface provides a fairly straightforward material media translation of a print bibliography with the added advantages of tagging and search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If others have suggestions for items to be added to this collection or simply want to share artifacts or resources related to the conversations of &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;, anyone can use twitter hashtags, my second channel for resource aggregation. Any tweets with #aproximatebible or #aproxibib are aggregated in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=#aproxibib OR #aproximatebible&quot;&gt;a proximate bible twitter search&lt;/a&gt;. This twitter channel has been an important interface for &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;, performing the values of collaboration, conversation, and a more radical material media translation of bibliography. You can get a flavor for this aggregation in the embedded twitter search below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Until very recently, I was using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rebelmouse.com/aproximatebible/&quot;&gt;rebelmouse&lt;/a&gt; to provide this community sourced tagged aggregation space using more channels than just twitter. Recently, rebelmouse has ended support for twitter hashtag sources except for Enterprise customers, which is cost prohibitive for this project. I will continue to look for a free or low cost option for multi-source media aggregation, but for now, twitter’s enhanced search API offers the necessary functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=#aproxibib OR #aproximatebible&quot; class=&quot;twitter-timeline&quot;&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;channels-twitter-facebook-email-rss&quot;&gt;channels (Twitter, Facebook, email, RSS)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the advantages of composing for the web is the ability to tap into the communication streams people use regularly to stimulate engagement with the project. Every time I release a new entry to &lt;a href=&quot;/aproximatebible&quot;&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/a&gt;, I push a notification to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.facebook.com/mphemenway&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/textpotential&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. For people who use RSS to manage feeds from sites that they monitor, my postach.io site provides a &lt;a href=&quot;http://aproximatebible.postach.io/feed.xml&quot;&gt;feed URL&lt;/a&gt; in the top right corner. Recently, I have added an &lt;a href=&quot;http://eepurl.com/bK7vGb&quot;&gt;email subscription&lt;/a&gt; option as well, since email is still the most organized and prevalent communication stream used by many in the academy. All of these channels offer interfaces with &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt; that shape the spaces and conversations that make this project what it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this map I have just detailed represents a proliferation of interfaces characteristic of our present new media age. Hopefully this challenges our tendencies toward consolidation, while providing many surfaces of contact with the community of conversation that is &lt;em&gt;a proximate bible&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 14:35:20 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/01/14/mapping-interfaces.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://textpotential.github.io/aproximatebible/2016/01/14/mapping-interfaces.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
